<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The propositions of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland as also the answer of the agents for the Protestants of Ireland made to the said propositions, and their petitions and propositions to His Majesty, and His Majesties answer to the propositions of the said Roman Catholicks, and the answer of James, Marquesse of Ormond, His Majesties Commissioner for the treatie and concluding of a peace in the kingdome of Ireland, to the said propositions.</title>
            <author>Confederate Catholics.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36692</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15987047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15987047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The propositions of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland as also the answer of the agents for the Protestants of Ireland made to the said propositions, and their petitions and propositions to His Majesty, and His Majesties answer to the propositions of the said Roman Catholicks, and the answer of James, Marquesse of Ormond, His Majesties Commissioner for the treatie and concluding of a peace in the kingdome of Ireland, to the said propositions.</title>
                  <author>Confederate Catholics.</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7-80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Waterford by Thomas Bourke, printer to the Confederated Catholicks of Ireland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Waterford, Ireland] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>THE PROPOSITIONS OF THE ROMAN CATHOLICKS OF IRELAND, Preſented by their Commiſſioners to His Sacred Majeſtie, in April, M. DC. XLIV.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the Anſwer of the Agents for the Proteſtants of Ireland, made to the ſaid Propoſitions; and their Petition and Propoſitions to His Majesty; with His Majeſties anſwer to the Propoſitions of the ſaid Roman Catholicks: And the anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of IAMES Marqueſſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond His Majeſties Commiſsioner for the treatie and concluding of a Peace in the Kingdome of Ireland, to the ſaid Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Waterford by</hi> Thomas Bourke, <hi>Printer to the Confederate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Catholicks of Ireland, M. DC. XLIV.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104672:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104672:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHereas the <hi>Supreme Councell</hi> of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Catholicks of Ireland, imployed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perſons of qualitie into England, authorized by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion to ſupplicate his Majeſtie, for redreſſe of the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the ſaid Catholicks, and to ſettle a firme peace in Church, and Commonwealth, who having then for ſome time attended His Majestie to that purpoſe, His Majeſties good intentions to the peace of this Kingdome, was for that preſent diverted, by the falſe Informations of perſons ill affected to this Nation, whoſe ſuggestions happened to be then listned unto, and anſwers accordingly given: So as the ſaid Commiſsioners returned into this Kingdome, with hopes onely, that His Majeſtie might in time bee better poſſeſſed of the power, and affections of His Catholicke ſubjects here, and of the uſe to be made thereof, His Majeſtie being pleaſed notwithstanding the ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations to give Commiſsion to the Lord Marques of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Lieutenant Generall of Ireland, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and concluding of the treatre, begun before His Majeſtie; In purſuance of which Commiſsion, the ſaid Catholicks preſented their propoſitions, the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance they first preſented to His Majestie in <hi>Oxford,</hi> unto which ſome anſwers were made, which being no way ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorie, were replied unto, and ſo the matter procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a long diſpute, &amp; debate, wherein many difficulties occurring, the treatie was adjourned, and ſo continues till
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104672:3"/> the tenth of <hi>Ianuary</hi> next, by which time His Majesties reſolution upon the whole matter repreſented unto him is expreſſed, &amp; a firme, &amp; lasting peace hoped for. This being the ſtate the treatie is in at this time, it may be conceived improper to give an account of the particular paſſages which are but overtures, and alterable, as it is well hoped, and little to bee doubted, but that in this they will bee, yet ſome to breed distraction and mistrusts among the ſaid Confederates, or blinded with private and ambitious ends, and impatient of any delay, have been ſo malicious, or mistaken, as to traduce the ſaid Confederate Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and their Commiſsioners affirming they might have obtained Conditions ſatisfactorie to any reaſonable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but that they rejected the ſame. To ſatisfie therefore all indifferent Iudgements that may enter into the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſaid proceedings, and to make it manifest, that the whole ſcope of the ſaid Catholicks was, and is for the freedome of the Nation in their Religion, Estates, and Liberties, with out trenching upon His Majesties rights, or other end, and that it may appeare how farre the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings hitherto come ſhort of that: It was thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to expoſe thoſe proceedings to publicke view, by putting them to the preſſe, ſo to caſt off thoſe aſperſions, that ignorant, or malicious perſons endeavour to cast upon them, having yet nevertheleſſe aſſured hopes that His Majesty will in time afford remedies to theſe Complaints, and with a gracious eye looke upon the ſufferings of this afflicted nation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="propositions">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104672:3"/>
            <head>The propoſitions of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland humbly preſented unto His Sacred Majestie, in purſueance of their Remonſtrance of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and to bee annexed to the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat all Acts made againſt the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Roman Catholicke Faith whereby any reſtrainte, penaltie, mulct, or incapacitie may bee layed upon any Roman Catholicke within the Kingdome of Ireland, may bee repealed, and the ſaid Catholicks to be allowed the freedome of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That your Majeſtie will bee pleaſed to call a free Parliament in the ſaid Kingdome, to bee held, and continued as in the ſaid Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance is expreſſed and the ſtatute of the tenth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, called Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings act, and all acts explayning, or enlarging the ſame be ſuſpended, during that parliament
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104672:4"/> for the ſpeedy ſettlement of the preſent affaires, and the repeale thereof to bee there further conſidered of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all acts, and ordinances made and paſſed in the now pretended parliament in that Kingdome ſince the ſeventh day of Auguſt 1641. be cleerely annulled, and declared voyd, and taken of the file.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That all Indictments, Attainders, Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawries, in the Kings Bench, or elſewhere ſince the ſaid ſeventh day of Auguſt 1641. And all letters pattents. grants, leaſes, cuſtodiums, bonds, recognizances, and all other records, act, or acts depending thereupon, or in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the ſaid Catholicks, or any of them bee taken off the files, annulled and declared void: firſt by your Majeſties publicke Proclamation, and after by act to be paſſed in the ſaid free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That inaſmuch as under collour of ſuch outlawries, and attainders, debts due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Catholickes have been granted, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed, or diſpoſed of, and of the other ſide, that debts due upon the ſaid Catholicks to thoſe of the adverſe partie have been levied, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to publicke uſe, that therefore all debts be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104672:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> by act of Parliament mutually releaſed, or, all to ſtand in <hi>ſtatu Quo.</hi> notwithſtanding any grant, or diſpoſition.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the late offices taken, or found upon fayned, or old titles ſince the yeare 1634. to intitle Your Majeſtie to ſeverall Countreyes in <hi>Connaght, Thomond,</hi> and in the Counties of <hi>Tipperarie, Lymmericke, Kilkenny,</hi> and <hi>VVickloe,</hi> be vacated, &amp; taken off the file, &amp; the poſſeſſors ſetled, &amp; ſecured in their ancient eſtates by act of Parliament. And that the like act of limitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of your Majeſties titles for the ſecuritie of the eſtates of your ſubjects of that Kingdome be paſſed in the ſaid parliament, as was enacted in the one and twenty yeare of his late Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raigne in this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That all Marckes of incapacitie impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the natives of that Kingdome to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or acquire lands, leaſes, offices, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments be taken away by act of parliament, and the ſame to extend to the ſecuring of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes, leaſes, or grants already made. And that for the education of youth an act be paſſed in the next parliament, for the erecting of one, or more Inns of Court, Vniverſities free, and common ſchooles.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104672:5"/> 8. That the offices, and places of command honour, profit, and truſt within that Kingdome be conferred upon Roman Catholicks natives in equalitie, and indifferencie with your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties other ſubjects.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the inſupportable oppreſſion of your ſubjects by reaſon of the Court of Wards, and reſpit of homage, be taken away, and a certaine revenue in lieu thereof ſetled upon your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie without diminution of your Majeſties profit.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That no Lord not eſtated in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or eſtated, and not reſident ſhall have vote in the ſaid parliament by proxie, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and none admitted to the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but ſuch as ſhall be eſtated, and reſident within the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That an act be paſſed in the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament declaratorie that the parliament of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is a free parliament of it ſelfe, independant of, and not ſubordinate, to the parliament of England: And that the ſubjects of Ireland are immediatly ſubject to your Majeſtie as in right of your Crowne: and that the members of the ſaid parliament of Ireland, and all other the ſubjects of Ireland are independant, and no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104672:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> way to bee ordered, or concluded by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England, and are onely to bee orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and governed within that Kingdome by your Majeſtie and ſuch Governors as are, or ſhall be there appointed, and by the parliament of that Kingdome according to the lawes of the land.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That the aſſumed power, or Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Councell-boord of determining all manner of cauſes, bee limitted to matters of ſtate, and all pattents, eſtates, and grants il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legally, and extrajudicially avoyded there, or elſewhere be left in ſtate as before, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties grieved, their heires, or aſſignes, till le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall eviction.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That the ſtatutes of the eleventh, twelfth, and thirteenth yeare of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſtapple-commodities be repealed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving unto your Majeſtie lawfull, and juſt pondage, and a booke of rates to bee ſetled by an indifferent Committee of both houſes, for all commodities.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That in as much as the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the chiefe governor, or governors of that Kingdome in that place of ſo great emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, and power, hath beene a principall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104672:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that much tyrannie, and oppreſſion hath beene exerciſed upon the ſubjects of that Kingdome. That your Majeſtie will bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to continue ſuch governors hereafter but for three yeares. And that none once imployed therein bee appointed for the ſame againe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the expiration of ſix yeares next after the end of the ſaid three yeares: And that an act paſſe to diſinable ſuch governor, or governors during their government, directly, or indire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, in uſe, truſt, or otherwiſe to make any manner of purchaſe, or acquiſition of any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, lands, tenements or hereditaments within that Kingdome, other then from your Majeſtie, your heires or ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That an act may be paſſed in the next parliament for the raiſing &amp; ſetling of trained bands within the ſeuerall Counties of that Kingdome, as well to prevent forraigne inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as to render them the more ſerviceable and ready for your Majeſties occaſions, as cauſe ſhall require.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That an act of oblivion be paſſed in the next free parliament to extend to all your Majeſties ſaid Catholicke ſubjects, and their adherents for all manner of offences, capitall;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104672:6"/> criminall, and perſonall: And the ſaid act to extend to all goods, and chattells, cuſtomes, maine-profits, prizes, arreares of rents taken, received, or incurred ſince theſe troubles.</p>
            <p n="17">17. For as much as your Majeſties ſaid Catholicke ſubjects have been taxed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inhuman cruelties which they never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, your Majeſties ſaid ſuppliants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for their vindication, and to manifeſt to all the world their deſire to have ſuch heynous offences puniſhed, and the offendors brought to Iuſtice, doe deſire, that in the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all notorious murders, breaches of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and inhuman cruelties, committed of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, may bee queſtioned in the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, if your Majeſtie ſo thinke fit, and ſuch as ſhall appeare to be guiltie to be excepted out of the ſaid act of oblivion, and puniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their deſerts.</p>
            <p>For as much DREAD SOVERAIGNE, as the wayes of our addreſſes unto your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie for apt remedies unto our grievances were hitherto debarred us, but now at length through your benigne grace and favour layd open, Wee doe humbly preſent theſe in purſuance of the ſaid Remonſtrance, which granted your ſaid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104672:7"/> ſubjects are ready to contribute the ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men as in their remonſtrance is ſpecified towards the ſuppreſſing of the unnaturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion now in this Kingdome: And will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expoſe their lives, and fortunes to ſerve your Majeſtie, as occaſions ſhall require.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_propositions">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:104672:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Anſwers of the Agents for the Proteſtants of Ireland, to the Propoſitions of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of Ireland, made in purſuance of his Sacred Majesties directions of the ninth of May</hi> 1644. <hi>requiring the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1, TO the firſt wee ſay that this hath beene the pretence of almoſt all thoſe who have entred into Rebellion in the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> at any time ſince the Reformation of Religion there which was ſetled by act of Parliament above eighty yeares ſince, and hath wrought good effect ever ſince, for the peace and welfare both of the Church and Kingdome there, and of the Church and Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and Proteſtant partie throughout all Chriſtendome, and ſo hath beene found wholeſome and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie by long experience, and the repealing of thoſe Lawes will ſet Popery againe both in juriſdiction, profeſſion, and practice, as it was before the ſaid Reformation, and introduce amongſt other inconveniences, the Supremacie of <hi>Rome,</hi> and take away, or much endanger your Majeſties Supreme and juſt authoritie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, a diminution of honour and power not to be endured. The ſaid acts extending aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to ſeditious ſectaries, as to popiſh Recuſants. So as by the repeale thereof, every man may ſeeme to be left to chooſe his owne Religion in that Kingdome which muſt needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get great confuſion, and the abounding of the Roman Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy there, hath beene one of the greateſt occaſions of this late Rebellion, Beſides it is humbly deſired that your Maieſtie will be pleaſed to take into your gracious Conſideration a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104672:8"/> clauſe in the act of Parliament paſt by your Majeſties Royall aſſent in <hi>England</hi> in the ſeventeenth yeare of your raigne tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching puniſhment to be inflicted upon thoſe that ſhall intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the authoritie of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> in any caſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas they deſire to have a free Parliament called, reflecteth by ſecret and cunning implication upon your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties preſent Parliament in <hi>Ireland</hi> as if it were not a free Parliament. Wee humbly beſeech your Majeſtie to reſent how dangerous it is to make ſuch inſinuation or intimation to your people of that kingdome touching that Parliament, wherein ſeverall acts of Parliament have already paſſed, the validitie where of may be endangered if the Parliament ſhould not be approved as a free Parliament, and it is a point of ſo high nature as we humbly conceive is not properly to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed but in Parliament. And your Majeſties ſaid Parliament now ſitting is a free Parliament in Law, holden before a perſon of honour and fortune in that Kingdome compoſed of good loyall, and well affected ſubjects to your Majeſtie, who doubtleſſe will be ready to comply in all things that ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be pious and juſt for the good of the true Proteſtant Religion, and for your Majeſties ſervice, and the good of the Church, and State, That if this preſent Parliament ſhould be diſſolved, it would be a great terrour, and diſcontent to all your Majeſties proteſtant ſubjects of that kingdome, and may be alſo a meanes to force many of your Majeſties ſubjects to quite that Kingdome, or peradventure to adhere to ſome other partie there in oppoſition of the Romiſh Iriſh confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, rather then be lyable to their power, which effects may prove of moſt dangerous conſequence, and we humbly offer to your Majeſties conſideration your owne gracious expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mentioned in the grounds and motives inducing your Majeſtie to agree to a Ceſſation of Armes for one whole yeare with the Roman Catholickes of <hi>Ireland</hi> Printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> the ninth of <hi>October</hi> 1642. <hi>viz.</hi> And let all our good ſubjects be aſſured that as we have for theſe reaſons, and with this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and deliberation conſented to this preparative to peace.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104672:8"/> And to that purpoſe doe continue our Parliament there, ſo we ſhall proceed in the accompliſhment thereof with that care, and circumſpection, that we ſhall not admit even peace it ſelfe other wiſe then as it may bee agreeable to conſcience, honour and juſtice. We alſo humbly deſire that ſuch Lawes as your Majeſtie ſhall thinke fit to paſſe may bee tranſmitted according to <hi>Poynings</hi> Law, and other lawes of explanation thereof, or of addition therevnto now in force with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and ſecuritie to your Majeſties proteſtant ſubjects. But if the preſent Parliament be diſſolved we humbly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto your Majeſtie that ſo many of your ableſt, and beſt proteſtant ſubjects have beene murdered, or baniſhed by this Rebellion, that few or no proteſtant Freeholders will be found in the Counties, Cities, and Burroughs to elect, and chooſe Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, which will be moſt dangerous to your Majeſties rights and prerogatives and good ſubjects, and may beget great diſputes in after times for the repealing of <hi>Poynings Act,</hi> notwithſtanding their faigned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of their loyaltie. Yet it plainely appeares they doe not repoſe ſucht ruſt inyour Majeſties Iuſtice as it becommeth lo yall ſubjects to doe, and ſuch they pretend themſelves to be, for that they ſeeke thereby to prevent your Majeſtie and your Councell of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland</hi> of ſo full a view, &amp; time of mature conſideration to be had of acts of Parliament of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> before they paſſe as in prudence is requiſit, and hath been found neceſſarie by the experience of well neere two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, And if their intentions were ſo cleare as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe wee know not why they ſhould avoyde the ſtricteſt view, and tryall of your Majeſties, and your Councels of both Kingdomes. This they deſire intending to introduce a great diminution of your Royall and neceſſarie power for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of your Regall State, and protection of your good proteſtant ſubjects there and elſewhere. And what ſpeciall uſe they ayme at in ſeeking ſuch repeale your proteſtant ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as they know not the particular ſo can they conjecture of none unleſſe the ſaid Confederates have ſome deſigne by way of ſurprize to obtrude upon your Majeſtie in their new
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104672:9"/> deſired Parliament ſome acts in Iuſtification of their ill done actions, and for condemning ſuch of your proteſtant ſubjects as have in their ſeverall degrees moſt faithfully ſerved your Majeſtie there, which we the rather beleeve ſeeing they have proved by their oath of Aſſociation, and the <hi>Bull</hi> lately pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince the Ceſſation, the deſtruction of the Proteſtants there, when they have their ſwords in their hands to put the ſame in execution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee humbly deſire that they may particularize thoſe orders or ordinances which may prejudice your Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. For we are well aſſured that the Parliament now ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Ireland</hi> on ſignification of your Majeſties pleaſure ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, eyther will give your Majeſtie full ſatisfaction, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale any unjuſt orders, or ordinances whatſoever, which may be prejudiciall to your Majeſtie. And there may be ſome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or ordinances which may concerne particular perſons in their lives, liberties, or fortunes, that may ſuffer unheard by the admitting of ſo generall a propoſition, which is meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propoſed, as wee humbly conceive to put a ſcorne on your Majeſties parliament now ſitting there, and to diſcourage your proteſtant ſubiects who have faithfully ſerved your Maieſty in that parliament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This wee conceive to be a very bold propoſition not warranted as we alſo conceive by any example, &amp; tending to introduce an ill preſident in after times, for it was never ſeene that Records were taken of the file but where there was ſome corruption, or fraud, or ſome illegall, or uniuſt carriage uſed in, and concerning the procuring, or making up of ſuch Records, and the ſame firſt well proved upon due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, And it may not onely conceale, but in ſome fort ſeeme to iuſtifie their abominable Treaſons, Murders, Cruelties, Maſſacres, and plunders acted againſt your Maieſties perſon Crowne and dignitie, upon the perſons of your Maieſties moſt loyall proteſtant ſubiects in that Kingdome, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Papiſts there to doe the like againe, beſides the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement it may beget in your Maieſties officers, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to their duties in the like inſurrections which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104672:9"/> hereafter, which alſo may prove very preiudiciall to your Maieſties rights and revenues, if the Records to ſupport the forfeytures wherein many of them are or may be grounded, ſhould be taken of the file, and Cancelled.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We humbly conceive that in times of peace, and moſt ſetled government. When the Court of Law and Iuſtice is moſt open, &amp; beſt obſerved, that the debts due to the Crowne and actually levied and payed in to your Maieſties uſe, ought not to bee reſtored though the Records of the forfeytures ſhould legally be reverſed, which is farre from the preſent caſe, And this propoſition tendeth to croſſe the juſt right of your Majeſtie, and to make the diſpoſition by the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate popiſh Rebels of debts due to proteſtants, and by the ſaid rebels by fraud and force levyed, and diſpoſed in maintenance of their rebellion, which commonly they call by the name of publicke uſes, to be in equall degree with the debts owing by the rebels and by them all forfeyted, and many of them by law duely levyed, which is a moſt unequall and unjuſt thing. And the ſaid propoſitions cannot, nor doth make offer to have the popiſh Confederats cut off from the debts due to them which they have juſtly forfeyted, but only for a colour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, to have the proteſtants looſe ſuch debts juſtly due to them, as have beene unjuſtly taken from them, who have done no act at all to forfeyte them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We know not of any offices found on fayned Titles, nor what the Confederats may demand in reſpect of any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces promiſed by your Majeſty, which we intend not, nor have any occaſion to diſpute, but do humbly conceive that all thoſe who have committed treaſon in the late rebellion ſubſequent to your Majeſties promiſe of thoſe graces, have thereby forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the benefit thereof together with the Lands which the ſaid graces, might elſe have related, and ſo their whole eſtates are now juſtly fallen to your Majeſty by their rebellion, which we conceive is of great importance for your Majeſties ſervice to be taken into conſideration, as firſt with regarde of the ſtatutes made in the preſent Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the neceſſarie encreaſe of your revenue decayed by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104672:10"/> the preſent rebellion. Thirdly the aboliſhing of the evill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Iriſh, and preſervation of Religion, Lawes and government there. Fourthly the ſatisfaction of your prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſubjects loſſes in ſome meaſure. Fiftly the arrears of your Majeſties Army, and other debts contracted for that war, &amp; for preſervation of that Kingdome to your Majeſtie. Sixtly the bringing in of more Brittiſh on the plantations. Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the building of ſome walled Townes in remote, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate places for the ſecuritie of that kingdome, and your good ſubjects there. Eightly the taking of the Natives from their former dependencie on their chiefetaynes who uſurped an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power on them to the diminution of your Regall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and to the oppreſſion of the inferiour.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This we conceive concerneth ſome of the late plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and no other part of that Kingdome, and that the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution herein mentioned is found to bee of great uſe eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the indifferencie of tryalls ſtrength of the government, and for trade and trafficke, and we humbly conceive that if other plantations ſhall not proceede for the ſetling, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that Kingdome, &amp; that no reſtraint be made of papiſts purchaſing, or buying of the proteſtants out of their former platations where they were prudently planted, though now caſt out of their eſtates by the late rebellion, &amp; unable to plant the ſame againe for want of meanes, and therefore probably upon eaſy tearmes will part with their eſtates to the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. That thoſe plantations will be deſtroyed to the great prejudice of your Maieſties ſervice, and endangering of the ſafety of that Kingdome. Touching bearing of offices we humbly conceive that their non-conformitie to the lawes and ſtatutes of that Realme is the onely marke of incapacity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon them. And wee humbly conceive that they ought not to expect to be more capable there then the Engliſh Natives are here in <hi>England</hi> in like caſe. For Schooles in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> there are divers ſetled in all parts of that Kingdome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by the Lawes and ſtatutes of that Realme. And if any perſon well affected ſhall erect, and endow any more ſchools there, at their owne charges, So that the Schoole-maſters and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104672:10"/> ſchollers may be governed according to the lawes, cuſtome, and orders of <hi>England,</hi> and the beſt of free ſcholes here. Wee cannot apprehend any iuſt exceptions thereunto, but touching Vniverſities, and Innes-of-Court. We humbly conceive that this part of the propoſition ſavoureth of ſome deſire to become independent upon <hi>England,</hi> or to make a ſeparation in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and lawes of the kingdome, which can never be truly happy but in the good unitie of both in the true proteſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and in the lawes of <hi>England.</hi> For as for matter of charge ſuch of the Natives as are deſirous to breede their ſonnes for learning in divinitie can be well content to ſend them to the Vniverſities of <hi>Lovain, Doway,</hi> and other places in forayne Kingdomes, and for Civill law or Phyſicke to <hi>Padua,</hi> &amp; other places which drawes a great treaſure yearely out of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions, but will ſend few, or none of them to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where they might as cheaply be brought up and become as learned, Which courſe we conceive is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den out of their pride and diſaffection towards this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the true Religion here profeſſed. And for the lawes of the land which are for the Common-lawes agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>England,</hi> ſo for the greateſt part of the ſtatutes, the Innes of Courts in <hi>England</hi> are ſufficient and the proteſtants come thither without grudging, And it is a meanes to civilize them after the Engliſh cuſtomes to make them familiar, and in love with the language, and Nation to preſerve law in the puritie when the profeſſors of it ſhall draw of one originall foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and ſee the manner of the practiſe of it in the ſame great Channell where his Majeſties Courts of Iuſtice of <hi>England</hi> doe flow cleerely. Whereas by ſeparations of the Kingdomes in the place of their principall inſtruction where their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in being are to be layd, a degenerate corruption, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Iuſtice may happily be introduced, and ſpred with much more difficultie to be corrected and reſtrayned after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by any diſcipline to be uſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or puniſhments there to be inflicted for departing from the true grounds of things that are beſt preſerved in unitie when they grow out of the ſame roote, then if ſuch Vniverſities and Innes of Court
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104672:11"/> as are propoſed ſhould be granted. All which wee humbly ſubmit to your Majeſties moſt pious and prudent Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Iudgement.</p>
            <p n="8">8. We humbly conceive that the Roman Catholicks Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in <hi>Ireland</hi> may have the like offices, and places as the Roman Catholickes Natives of <hi>England</hi> here have, and not otherwiſe. Howbeit we conceive that in the generallity they have not deſerved ſomuch by their late rebellion. Therefore we ſee not why they ſhould be endowed with any new or further capacity or priviledges then they have by the Lawes, and ſtatutes now in force in that Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Wee know no oppreſſion by reaſon of the Court of Wards, and wee humbly conceive that the Court of wards is of great uſe for the rayſing of your Majeſties revenues, the preſervation of your Maieſties Tennures, and chiefly the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Gentry in the proteſtant Religion, and civilitie of learning, and good manners who otherwiſe would bee brought up in ignorance, &amp; barbariſme, their eſtats be ruyned by their kindred, and friends, and continue their dependance on the chiefe Lords to the great preiudice of your Maieſties ſervice and proteſtant ſubiects, and there being no colour of exception to your Maieſties iuſt Title to wardſhips, we know not why the taking away of Court concerning the ſame ſhould be ſo preſſed, unleſſe it be to prevent the education of the Lords and Gentry that fall-wards in the proteſtant reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, For that part of this propoſition which concernes reſpit of homage, we humbly conceive it reaſonable that ſome way may be ſetled for this, if it ſtands with your Maieſties good pleaſure, without preiudice to your Maieſty, or your prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubiects.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Wee humbly conceive that in the yeare 1641. by the graces which your Majeſtie then granted to your ſubjects of Ireland, the matter of this propoſition was in a faire way regulated by your utter aboliſhing of blancke proxies, &amp; limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Lords preſent, and attending in the Parliament of Ireland that no one of them ſhould be capable of more proxies then two, and preſcribing the Peeres of that Kingdome not there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104672:11"/> reſident to purchaſe fitting proportions of land in Ireland within five yeares from the laſt of Iuly 1641. or elſe to looſe votes till they ſhould make ſuch purchaſe: which purchaſe by reaſon of the troubles happening in that Kingdome, &amp; which have continued for two yeares, and a halfe, have not perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture yet beene made. And therefore your Majeſtie may now bee pleaſed, and may take juſt occaſion to inlarge the time, when that Kingdome may againe be ſetled in a happy and firme peace: And as to members of the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the ſame is moſt fit as wee humbly conceive to be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the Lawes, and ſtatutes of that Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This propoſition concernes your Majeſties high Court of Parliament both of England and Ireland, and is beyond our abilities who are not acquainted with the Records, and preſidents of this nature to give an anſwer unto, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Wee humbly deſire your Majeſties pardon for not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto the ſame.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The Councell-Table hath alwayes exerciſed Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in ſome caſes ever ſince the Engliſh government was ſetled in that Kingdome, and is of ſo long continuance in caſes of ſome natures, as the beginning thereof appeareth not, which ſeemeth to bee by preſcription and hath alwayes beene armed with power to examen upon oath as a Court of Iuſtice, or in nature of a Court of Iuſtice in caſes of ſome natures, and may bee very neceſſary ſtill in many Caſes, eſpecially for the preſent, till your Majeſties Lawes may more generally be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in that Kingdome: And wee conceive that Board is ſo well limitted by printed Inſtructions in your Maieſties Royall fathers, and by your Majeſties Grace in the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeare of your Raigne, that it needeth for the preſent little, or no further regulating at all: Howbeit they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly referre unto your Majeſties great wiſdome, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to doe therein, as to Law and Iuſtice ſhall apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The matter of this propoſition is ſetled in a fitting and good way by your Majeſtie already, as wee conceive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Graces granted by your Majeſtie to your people
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104672:12"/> of Ireland in the ſeventeenth yeare of your Raigne, to which we humbly referre our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Wee humbly conceive that this propoſition tendeth to lay a falſe and ſcandalous aſperſion upon your Majeſties gracious government over Ireland: And that it trencheth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high upon your Wiſdome, Iuſtice and Power, &amp; under col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſuppoſed corruptions pretended to bee in the greateſt Officer that commandeth under your Majeſtie there, if hee continue ſo long in his governement as may well enable him to find out and diſcover the true ſtate of that Kingdome, and the dangerous diſpoſitions and deſignes of the Popiſh partie there, to prevent him therein; and to turne him out from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſervice before, or as ſoone, as hee is throughly informed, and experienced how to doe the ſame, and then to hold him excluded ſo long that in all likelyhood hee ſhall not live to come to that place the ſecond time, which wee humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will bee a great diſcouragement to any perſon of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fortune to ſerve your Majeſtie in that high truſt: And for the purchaſing lands in that Kingdome, your Majeſtie may bee pleaſed to leave them to the Lawes, and puniſh them ſeverely if they commit any offence, or exerciſe any oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under collour of purchaſing of any lands or eſtates what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The having of trained bands in Ireland for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent cannot under favour be for your Majeſties ſervice or the ſafetie of that Kingdome<hi>:</hi> For that the Proteſtants by the ſad effects of the late Rebellion are ſo much deſtroyed that the ſaid bands muſt conſiſt in effect altogether of the Confederate Catholicks, and to continue them in armes ſtored with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and made ready for ſervice by muſtering, and often training, will prove under collour of advancing your Majeſties ſervice againſt forraigne invaſion, a meere guard and power over popiſh forces always in readineſſe to protect the Popiſh Confederates, and by force, and Armes according to their late oath and proteſtations to execute all their cruell deſignes for extirpation of the Proteſtant Religion and Engliſh Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both which they mortally hate; Howſoever in cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104672:12"/> they diſſemble it, and to prevent the ſetling an armie of good Proteſtants, without which your Maieſties good ſubiects cannot live ſecurely there.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Wee humbly pray, that the Lawes of force bee taken into conſideration, And doe humbly conceive that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in honour and Iuſtice may forbeare to diſcharge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe any actions, ſuites, debts, or intereſts whereby your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties proteſtant ſubiects who have committed no offence againſt your Maieſtie or your Lawes ſhould be barred or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of any of their legall remedies or iuſt demands which by any of your Maieſties Lawes and ſtatutes they may have againſt the popiſh Confederates (who are the onely delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents) or any of their party for or in reſpect of any wrongs done unto them, or any their anceſtors, or predeceſſors, in or concerning their Lands, goods, or eſtates ſince the contryving or breaking forth of the rebellion, The ſaid Confederates ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving without provocation ſhed ſo much innocent bloud, and acted ſo many cruelties as cannot be parralleled in any ſtorie, And we conceive it to be high preſumption in them upon ſo weake grounds to propound an act of oblivion in ſuch gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall termes, ſome of the Confederates having beene contry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or actors of ſuch cruell murders and other acts of in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie as cry to God, and your Sacred Maieſtie for Iuſtice, And they having of your Maieſties Revenues, cuſtomes, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides and other rights of your Crowne in their hands or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by them to the value of twenty hundred thouſand pounds and more.</p>
            <p n="17">17. We conceive this propoſition is made but for a floriſh, &amp; if the Confederates be ſo deſirous to try their innocencie as they pretend they need not ſtay for another Parliament in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but ſubmit to that which is now in being, which is an equall and iuſt Parliament, as in ſome of your reaſons touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that point is expreſſed, and they offering to draw it to a new Parliament, is in effect to deſire that they may be their owne Iudges, for as that Kingdome is now imbroyled and waſted, the chiefe delinquents, or Confederates will be ſo prevalent a faction in the next Parliament, that they will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104672:13"/> be able, and doubtleſſe will cleere all the popiſh party how guilty ſoever, and condemne all the proteſtants how innocent ſoever.</p>
            <p>Theſe anſwers to the high, and unexpected demands of the Confederates, we have framed in humble obedience, to your Maieſties directions, but being very ſenſible as of the weight and great importance of the buſineſſe ſo alſo of our owne weakeneſſe and want of time, and well knowing that ſome of your Privy Counſellors, Iudges, and Officers of that Kingdome are now in Towne ſent for over, and here atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by your Maieſties command, who by their long obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and experience of the affaires and ſtate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are better able to give your Maieſtie more full and ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry anſwers touching the premiſſes then we can, And concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the Collections in Anſwer to the ſaid Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates Remonſtrance, which wee humbly preſented to your Maieſty the 27. of the laſt moneth of <hi>April,</hi> may in many things give your Maieſty more light then theſe our anſwers doe or can. Wee humbly beſeech your Maieſty that the ſaid privy Counſellors, ludges, and Officers as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire may bee called upon and heard to give your Maieſty the better ſatisfaction in theſe particulars, and that to the ſame purpoſe the Booke of the ſaid Collections may be peruſed, and conſidered of, as your Maieſtie ſhall finde moſt requiſit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104672:13"/>
            <head>The humble petition of divers of your Maieſties Proteſtant ſubiects in your Kingdome of Ireland, as well Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of your Maieſties Army here, as others whoſe names are ſubſcribed in the behalfe of themſelves, and other your Proteſtant ſubiects in this your Kingdome.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Kings moſt Excellent Majestie.</head>
            <p>SHeweth, that this your Highneſſe Kingdome, reduced with a vaſt expence of treaſure, and much effuſion of Brittish blood, to the obedience of the Imperiall Crowne of England, hath been by the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care of your progenitors, eſpecially of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and of your Royall Father of ever bleſsed memory, and your ſacred Majesty in many parts happily planted, great ſummes of moneyes disburſed in building and improvements, Churches edified, and endowed, and frequented with multitudes of Protestants, and your Cuſtome, and revenues raiſed to great yearely ſummes, by the induſtry of your Proteſtant ſubjects eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and great ſummes of moneis by way of ſubſidies, and contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cheerfully payed unto your Majeſtie by your ſaid ſubjects, in which happineſse this your Kingdome hath flourished in a long continued peace, and under your highneſse most glorious, and happy governement, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that by the preſent generall rebellion and conſpiracy, raiſed out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of your bleſſed Governement, and for the rooting out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and ſo for the diſpoſſeſsing of your Majesty of this your ſaid Kingdome, without the leaſt occaſion offered by your Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or the Proteſtant ſubjects; And notwithstanding that your Majeſty immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before had enlarged beyond preſident your Royall favour and bounty to them in granting all that their and our joint Agents did deſire of your Majeſty, and wee continuing amongſt them in all love and amity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtruſt your petitioners and others who laboured to oppoſe thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104672:14"/> damnable deſignes and practices have been driven from their dwelling, estates, and fortunes, their houſes, and Churches, burnt, and demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, all monuments of civillity utterly defaced your Majesties Forts and places of defence throwne downe, and the Common, and ſtatute lawes of this your Kingdome utterly confounded, by taking on themſelves the exerciſe of all manner of authorities, and Iuriſdictions Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Civill, both by land and ſea, proper and particular to your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty being your just prerogatives, and the Royall flowers of your Imperiall Diademe, to the disheriſon of your Crowne, and your royall revenues brought to nothing; And the Protestant Clergie with their Revenues, and ſupport for the preſent destroyed This your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in all parts formerly inhabited by Brittish Protestants now depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated of them, and many thouſands of your Protestant moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly uſed, ſtripped naked, tortured, famished, hanged, buried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, drowned, and otherwiſe (by all barbarous cruell ſorts of death) muthered, and ſuch as yet remaine alive of them are reduced to that extremity, that very few of them have wherewithall to maintaine a being; And all of them ſo terrified and afflicted, with thoſe barbarous and inhuman cruelties, the true reports whereof being now ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the Chriſtian world, your ſuppliants conceives feares, your Majeſties Brittish ſubjects will be diſcouraged from coming againe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite this Kingdome: And the remnant of the Brittish left here will bee forced to depart; All this being done by the Conſpiracy of the Papists who did publickely declare the utter extirpation of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and all the Brittish profeſsors thereof out of this your Majeſties Kingdome, and to the end this may the better in ſome meaſure appeare, your ſuppliants have made choice of Captaine <hi>M. William Ridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Hamilton</hi> Knight and Barronet, Captaine <hi>Michael Iones,</hi> and M. <hi>Fenton Parſons</hi> whom they have imployed and authorized as their Agents, to manifeſt the truth thereof, in ſuch particulars as for the preſent they are furnished withall, referring the more ample manifestation thereof to the ſaid Captaine M. <hi>William Ridgeway,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Hamilton,</hi> Captaine <hi>Iones,</hi> and <hi>Fenton Parſons,</hi> or any three or more of them, and ſuch other Agents as shall with all convenient ſpeed bee ſent as occaſion shall require to attend your Majesty from the Proteſtant ſubjects of the ſeverall Provinces of this your Kingdome.</p>
            <p>VVee therefore your Majeſties most humble, loyall and obedient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104672:14"/> Proteſtant ſubjects caſting downe our ſelves at your Royall feete, and flying to you for ſuccour and redreſse in our great calamity as our most gracious Soveraigne Lord and King, and next and immediatly under Almighty God our protector and defender, moſt humbly beſeeching your Sacred Majeſtie to admit into your Royall preſence from time to time our ſaid Agents, and in your great wiſedome to take into your Princely care, and conſideration the diſtreſſed estates and humble deſires of your ſaid ſubjects, for that the glory of God your Maieſties honour, and the happineſſe of your good ſubiects the Proteſtant Religion may be reſtored through the whole Kingdome to its luſter, and the loſses of your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubiects may be repayred in ſuch manner, and meaſure as your Maieſtie in your Princely wiſedome shall thinke fit, and that this your Kingdome may be ſo ſetled as that your ſaid Proteſtant ſubiects may hereafter live therein under the happy government of your Maieſtie and your Royall posteritie, with comfort and ſecuritie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereby your Maiestie will render your ſelfe throughout the whole world a most iuſt and glorious defender of the Proteſtant Religion, and draw downe a bleſsing on all other your Royall undertakings for which your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners will ever pray, &amp;c.</p>
            <list>
               <head>A liſt of the names of thoſe who have underwritten their names to this petition.</head>
               <item>GEorge Kildare.</item>
               <item>Montgomerye.</item>
               <item>H. Blany.</item>
               <item>VV. Ridgeway.</item>
               <item>Ia. Montgomery.</item>
               <item>Cha. Coote.</item>
               <item>Fra. Hamilton.</item>
               <item>Arthur Forbis.</item>
               <item>Robert Han'y.</item>
               <item>Fra. Slinsby.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Colley.</item>
               <item>Arthur Blundell.</item>
               <item>Ia. Dunbar.</item>
               <item>Ed Powey.</item>
               <item>Tho. Meredith.</item>
               <item>Arthur Loftus.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Vsher.</item>
               <item>Geo. Monke.</item>
               <item>Francis VVilloughby.</item>
               <item>Robert Sterling.</item>
               <item>Io. Morris.</item>
               <item>Henry Iones.</item>
               <item>Io. Piggot.</item>
               <item>Robert Bayly.</item>
               <item>Fra. Moore.</item>
               <item>Ed Philpot.</item>
               <item>VV. Parſons Iunior.</item>
               <item>Arthur Culme.</item>
               <item>Eraſmus Burrowes.</item>
               <item>Io. Edgeworth.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Dodwell.</item>
               <item>Io. Newman.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Plunket.</item>
               <item>Io Ferrar.</item>
               <item>Io. Cliffe.</item>
               <item>Peter VVybrants.</item>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104672:15"/>
               <item> Theod. Scout.</item>
               <item>Brean Stapleton.</item>
               <item>Da. Dunbar.</item>
               <item>Tho Nill.</item>
               <item>Geo. Lawnder.</item>
               <item>Hen. Tillier.</item>
               <item>Hugh Cogh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</item>
               <item>VVilliam Gilbert.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Montgomery.</item>
               <item>Ia. Calvill.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Iohnſon.</item>
               <item>Geo. Montgomery.</item>
               <item>Robert VVh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>field.</item>
               <item>Io. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bell.</item>
               <item>Hugh Montgomery.</item>
               <item>Io Rayvan.</item>
               <item>Ioſaa VVheeler.</item>
               <item>Arch Hamilton.</item>
               <item>VVilliam VVhite.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Piggot.</item>
               <item>Tho. Tully.</item>
               <item>Roger Atkinſon,</item>
               <item>Nich<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Simpſon,</item>
               <item>Oli VVheeler.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Alsry.</item>
               <item>Adam Meredith.</item>
               <item>Tho. Coote.</item>
               <item>Edw Piggot.</item>
               <item>Ia. Deroaile.</item>
               <item>Geo Boothe.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Knight.</item>
               <item>Robert Sanderſon.</item>
               <item>Ia. Starling.</item>
               <item>An. Dopping.</item>
               <item>Radeliffe Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kinfield.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Tho. Leigh.</item>
               <item>Dan. Heſter.</item>
               <item>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivall.</item>
               <item>Ia. Crawford.</item>
               <item>Stephen Allen.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Anberry.</item>
               <item>Iohn Doyle.</item>
               <item>Edw. Spring.</item>
               <item>Io. Iohnſon.</item>
               <item>Tho. Almer.</item>
               <item>Io. Hoy.</item>
               <item>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ennedy.</item>
               <item>Cooley <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Robert Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Robert Stewar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Tho. VVhite.</item>
               <item>Pat. Connemag.</item>
               <item>Dudley Colley.</item>
               <item>Nic. Pinnar.</item>
               <item>Sa Mull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nax.</item>
               <item>Ia. Kennedy.</item>
               <item>Hen. Kenney.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Hamilton.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Billing.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Vmphry.</item>
               <item>Hugh Ionne.</item>
               <item>Io. Leight.</item>
               <item>Andr Brereton.</item>
               <item>Io Clerke.</item>
               <item>Roger Holland.</item>
               <item>Io. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erring.</item>
               <item>Mar. Higginſon.</item>
               <item>Io. VValler.</item>
               <item>Iohauth Holt.</item>
               <item>Edw. Fisher Capt.</item>
               <item>Tho. Lewton.</item>
               <item>Tho. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nley.</item>
               <item>Ioſ. Holt.</item>
               <item>Io. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mberlege.</item>
               <item>And. Cumble.</item>
               <item>Geo. Chibaldiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Io. Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Fra Barſer.</item>
               <item>Nath. Stoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>VVill. Boding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</item>
               <item>And. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>g.</item>
               <item>Edw. Barten.</item>
               <item>Io. Pinroſe.</item>
               <item>VVill Richardſon.</item>
               <item>Robert Maſſon.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Heward.</item>
               <item>Ia. VVoodcocke.</item>
               <item>And. VVatſon.</item>
               <item>Robert Iones.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Tedder.</item>
               <item>And. Iones.</item>
               <item>Robert Boyer.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Medcalfe.</item>
               <item>Iona. Coſtie.</item>
               <item>VVilliam Sands.</item>
               <item>Natha. Poſter.</item>
               <item>Io. Field.</item>
               <item>VValter Fraſter.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_propositions">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104672:15"/>
            <head>His Majesties anſwer, to the propoſitions of the Roman Catholicks of Ireland.</head>
            <p>COncerning any thing in Religion, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties anſwer is, That as the Lawes againſt thoſe of the Romiſh Religion, within that his Kingdome of Ireland have never been execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any rigour or ſeverity: So if ſuch his ſubjects ſhall by returning to their duty and loyalty, merit his Majeſties favour and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, they ſhall not for the future have cauſe to complaine, that leſle moderation is uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, then hath been in the moſt favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi> his times<hi>:</hi> Provided that under pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they doe not ſtirre up ſedition but live quietly and peaceably according to their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Touching the calling a free Parliament (by which his Majeſtie ſuppoſes the propoſers intend a new Parliament) his Majeſtie ſayes he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104672:16"/> could wiſh, that all the particulars might bee fully agreed on, and ratified this Parliament; his Majeſtie well underſtanding that his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubjects may bee in farre greater danger in a new Parliament then the propoſers and their Party can bee in this, his Majeſtie being willing to give them any ſecurity that can bee deſired againſt their apprehenſions; however ſince ſome objections and doubts are raiſed of the legall continuance of this Parliament ſince the death of the Lord Deputy <hi>VVansford,</hi> and by the late arrivall of his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, after the day of meeting upon the prorogation (though thoſe doubts may bee eaſily ſolved) his Majeſtie is content to call a new Parliament, upon condition, that all particulars bee firſt agreed on, and the Acts to be paſſed bee firſt tranſmitted, according to cuſtome (for his Majeſtie will by no meanes conſent the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Poynings</hi> Act) and the propoſers giving his Majeſtie ſecurity, that there ſhall be no attempt in that Parliament to paſſe any other Act, then what is agreed on, &amp; firſt tranſmitted; or to bring any other preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to any of his Majeſties Proteſtant ſubjects there.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104672:16"/> 3. His Majeſtie neither can nor will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Acts in themſelves lawfull to bee voyd, but is content that neither the Propoſers, nor their party ſhall ſuffer any pejudice by any Acts or Ordinances paſſed, ſince the time in that propoſition mentioned, by reaſon of this commotion: And for that end ſhall give his full concurrence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The matters of the foure, five and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Propoſitions are to bee digeſted into an Act of Oblivion, in which his Majeſtie will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Clauſes to enlarge his mercy: but will not by declaring Indictments legally taken &amp; regularly proſecuted to be voyd, give any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to, or make any excuſe for the preſent Rebellion: which would be a great prejudice to truth, and to the future ſecurity of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And therefore His Majeſtie is content to grant a full and generall Pardon to all perſons whatſoever within that his Kingdome (except for all Treaſons, Rebellion, or other crimes whatſoever, growing or ariſing from or by reaſon of the ſaid Rebellion) &amp; will likewiſe give his conſent to ſuch an Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion as ſhall be prepared &amp; tranſmitted to him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104672:17"/> by the adviſe of his Lord Lieutenant &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Ireland, who are fitteſt to conſider in what ſtate debts are to bee left: and particular actions and remedies to bee waved: in which His Majeſtie for the peace of the Kingdome will bee content to releaſe what concernes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When all particulars ſhall bee agreed on, and faithfully executed on the parts of the Propoſers, his Majeſtie (expecting a juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of his bountie, as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he parts with very much, to which hee hath a legall and undoubted title) is content to releaſe and quit his right to all ſuch lands in the Counties mentioned (except within the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of Kilkenny and Wickloe) upon the tearmes formerly aſſented by his Majeſtie in his Anſwer to the grievanees in the ſeventeenth yeare of his Raigne, and will conſent to ſuch an Act of limitations as is deſired.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When all other things ſhall bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, his Majeſtie will conſent to an Act for the taking away any incapacity, as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, either to lands or offices, if any ſuch there bee: And will willingly conſent to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104672:17"/> erecting an Innes of Court, Vniverſity, or free-ſchooles, provided that they bee gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſuch Statutes, and Orders, as His Majeſtie ſhall approve, and agreable to the Cuſtome of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Such of His Majeſties ſubjects of the Romiſh Religion within that Kingdome, as ſhall manifeſt their dutie and Affection to His Majeſtie, ſhall receive ſuch marks of His Majeſties favour in offices and places of truſt, as ſhall manifeſt His Majeſties good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and regard of them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. His Majeſtie will take care, that his good ſubjects of that Kingdome ſhall not be oppreſſed by his Court of Wards, and if op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of that kind have been, upon good and due information, His Majeſtie will cauſe Iuſtice to be done for the time paſt; and for the future will prevent the like by Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But for the taking away of that Court, His Majeſtie can make no anſwer, till the particulars for his ſatisfaction bee ſet downe, and preſented to him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. His Majeſtie conſented as farre as is fit for him in this Point, in his anſwer to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104672:18"/> the five and twentieth grievance, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth yeare of his Raigne; the which he is ſtill willing ſhall bee enacted, looking for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtill to five yeares, to begin after the peace concluded.</p>
            <p n="11">11. His Majeſtie conceives the ſubſtance of this Propoſition (which concernes the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Rights of both Kingdomes) fit to bee referred to the free debate and expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the two parliaments, when it ſhall pleaſe God that they may freely and ſafely ſit, His Majeſtie being ſo equally concerned in the priviledges of either, that hee will take care to the utmoſt of his power, that they ſhall both conteine themſelves within their proper limitts: his Majeſtie being the Head, and equally intereſſed in the Rights of both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This is ſufficiently provided for in his Majeſties Anſwer to the tenth grievance, which hee is content ſhall paſſe.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Since it appeares by long experience that theſe Lawes have not produced that good effect for which they were made, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie was graciouſly pleaſed by his late Graces,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104672:18"/> that thoſe Statutes ſhould bee repealed, ſave onely for woolls and woollfells: and will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame reſolution<hi>:</hi> And a Booke of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhall bee ſetled by an indifferent Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee.</p>
            <p n="14">14. His Majeſtie doth not admit that the long continuance of the Chiefe Governor of that Kingdome in that place, hath been an occaſion of much tyranny and oppreſſion, or that any tyranny, or oppreſſion hath been exerciſed upon his ſubjects in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: However his Maieſtie will take care, that ſuch Governors, ſhall not continue longer in choſe places, then hee ſhall find for the good of his people there: and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that they ſhall bee inhibited to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny purchaſe (other then by leaſe, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of their Houſes) during the ſpace of their Goverment, in ſuch manner as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
            <p n="15">15. This propoſition is to be explayned, and ſome particular wayes to bee propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his Maieſtie for the doing thereof<hi>:</hi> And then his Maieſtie upon due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſafety and ſecurity of his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104672:19"/> Subiects, will returne his Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Anſwered in the fourth and fifth.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Such perſons who ſhall be excepted out of the Act of Oblivion, ſhall bee tryed by the knowne Lawes of the Land.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_propositions">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104672:19"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of IAMES Marques of Ormond His Majeſties Commiſsioner, for the treaty, and concluding of a Peace in this Kingdome, for and in the name and behalfe of His Majeſtie to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of His Roman Catholicke ſubjects of Ireland.</head>
            <p>VVHen all the particular demands made on the behalfe of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the Church, and his Majeſties Proteſtant ſubjects, and their party ſhall be concluded, his Maieſtie will bee graciouſly pleaſed on his part, to agree to the particulars hereafter expreſſed <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To the firſt propoſition, his Majeſtie will bee graciouſly pleaſed, if his ſaid Roman Catholicke ſubjects ſhall by their obedience, and loyaltie merit his Majeſties favour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, that they ſhall not for the future have cauſe to complaine, that leſſe moderation is uſed towards them then hath been in the moſt favourable of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp; King <hi>Iames</hi> his times; But his Maieſtie for divers waighty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104672:20"/> conſiderations will further adviſe, before hee conſent to the repeale of any the Acts, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſaid Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the ſecond, his Majeſtie will bee graciouſly pleaſed to call a new Parliament up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, that all particulars therein to bee paſſed by act of Parliament, be firſt agreed on, betweene us his Majeſties Commiſſioner, and <hi>Donogh</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskery, Alexandermac Donell,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Plunket</hi> Eſquiers, Sir <hi>Robert Talbot</hi> Baronet, <hi>Dermot O Brien, Patricke Darcy, Geffrey Browne,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Dillon</hi> Eſquiers, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny five or more of them, who are deputed by his ſaid Roman Catholicke ſubjects, to treate with Vs about the ſame<hi>:</hi> And the ſaid Acts ſo agreed upon bee tranſmitted according to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acts of parliament in that behalfe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, And that there ſhall be no attempt by his Majeſties Roman Catholicke ſubjects in that parliament to paſſe any other act, then what is agreed upon as aforeſaid and firſt tranſmitted, or to bring any other prejudice to any of his Maieſties proteſtant ſubiects in this kingdome: And if any thing ſhall be attempted in the ſaid parliament to the contrarie, that then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Lieutenant, or other Chiefe Governor, or Governors, before whom the ſaid parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104672:20"/> ſhall be holden, ſhall forthwith after ſuch attempt, diſſolve the ſaid Parliament without expecting any further direction from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie for the ſame; But his Majeſtie for divers waightie conſiderations, will bee further advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, before that he doe conſent to the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Poynings</hi> Act.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the third, his Majeſtie will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed that none of his ſaid Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke ſubjects, ſhall ſuffer any prejudice by any Acts or Ordinances paſſed in this preſent Parliament ſince the time in the Propoſition mentioned, by reaſon of the preſent commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but his Majeſtie cannot legally declare Acts or Ordinances made in Parliament which are in themſelves lawfull; to be voyde, nor give warrant to take them off the file.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the fourth his Majeſtie cannot in courſe of Iuſtice, by his Proclamation declare indictments, attaintures, out-lawries, Letters-patents, Grants, Leaſes, Bonds, Recognizances, or any other legall record to be voyde, or taken off the file, But his Majeſtie will be graciouſly pleaſed to grant a full and Generall pardon, to all perſons whatſoever, excepting ſuch as hereafter upon this treaty, ſhalbe thought fit to be left thereout, for all Treaſons, rebellions and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104672:21"/> other crimes whatſoever, growing and ariſing for or by reaſon of the ſame, And will likewiſe give his conſent, that an act bee paſſed to that purpoſe, in which his Majeſtie will admit any clauſes to enlarge his mercy, And his Majeſtie will be further graciouſly pleaſed to determine all cuſtodiums which have beene granted ſince the 22. of <hi>October</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To the fift propoſition his Majeſty can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in Iuſtice conſent to the taking away of any debts due to his ſubjects, who have committed no offence which might occaſion the forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof, But for ſuch debts as have accrued unto his Majeſtie by the attaynture or fugacie of any of his Majeſties Roman Catholicke ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſince the 23. of October 1641. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie will be graciouſly pleaſed to remit ſo many of them, as have not beeen payed into his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Exchequer or received otherwiſe to his Maieſties uſe, or by his appointment.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To the ſixt propoſition his Maieſty will be graciouſly pleaſed to releaſe and quite his right to all ſuch lands in the ſaid propoſition mentioned, except within the Counties of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenny and Wickloe, upon the Termes former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſented unto by his Maieſtie in his anſwer to the grievances in the 17. yeare of his raigne, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104672:21"/> will conſent to ſuch an act of limitation, as is deſired.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To the ſeventh his Maieſty will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed to conſent to an act, for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away any incapacitie as Natives, eyther to lands or offices, if any ſuch there be, and will willingly conſent to the erecting of an Innes of Court, Vniverſitity or free-ſchooles, Provided that they be governed by ſuch ſtatutes, rules, and orders, as his Maieſty ſhall approve, and be agreable to the Cuſtomes of England.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To the eight his Maieſty will be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed that ſuch of his Maieſties ſaid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects within this kingdome as ſhall manifeſt their dutie and affection to his Maieſty ſhall receive ſuch markes of his Maieſties favour in offices and places of truſt, as ſhall manifeſt his Maieſties good acceptance, and regarde of them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To the ninth propoſition, his Maieſtie will take care, that his good ſubiects of this kingdome ſhall not be oppreſſed by his Court of Wards, And if oppreſſions of that kinde have beene upon good and due information, his Maieſty will cauſe Iuſtice to be done for the time paſt, and for the future will prevent the like by inſtructions. But for the taking away
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104672:22"/> of that Court, his Majeſty can make no anſwer, till the particulars for his ſatisfaction bee ſet downe and preſented unto him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. To the tenth Propoſition, his Majeſtie conſented as farre as is fit for him in this point, in his anſwer to the 25 grievance, in the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeare of his raigne the which hee is ſtill willing ſhalbe enacted, looking forwards ſtill to five yeares, to begin after the peace concluded.</p>
            <p n="11">11. To the eleventh Propoſition his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty conceives the ſubſtance of this Propoſition (which concerneth the fundamentall rights of both kingdomes) fit to bee referred to the free debate, and expoſtulation of the two Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when it ſhall pleaſe God, that they may freely and ſafely ſit his Majeſty being ſo equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned in the priviledges of eyther, that he will take care to the uttermoſt of his power, that they ſhall both contayne themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their proper limits, his Majeſtie being the head and equally concerned in the rights of both.</p>
            <p n="12">12. To the twelfth his Majeſtie hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently provided for this, in his anſwer to the tenth grievanee, which his Majeſtie is content ſhall paſſe by act of parliament.</p>
            <p n="13">13. To the thirteenth propoſition his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104672:22"/> hath beene pleaſed by his late Graces that thoſe ſtatutes ſhould be repealed, ſave onely for Wools and wool-fels, And is well pleaſed, that the ſame be done by act of parliament, and that a Booke of Rates be ſetled, by indifferent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners.</p>
            <p n="14">14. To the foureteenth propoſition his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie doth not admit or beleeve, that the long continuance of the chiefe Covernors of this kingdome in their places of government, hath beene an occaſion of any tyrany or oppreſſion, or that any tyrany or oppreſſion hath beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed upon his ſubjects of this his kingdome, howſoever his Majeſty will be graciouſly pleaſed to take care, that ſuch Governors ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue longer in thoſe places, then he ſhall finde for the good of his people here, And his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie is content, that they ſhall bee inhibited to make any purchaſe, other then by Leaſe for the proviſion of their houſes during the time of their government.</p>
            <p n="15">15. To the fifteenth Propoſition, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is to be explaned, and ſome particular way to be propoſed for the doing thereof, And then conſideration being had of the ſafety and ſecuritie of his Majeſties proteſtant ſubjects, an anſwer will be made therevnto.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104672:23"/> 16. To the ſixteenth propoſition, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie cannot in Iuſtice to the forecloſing of the ſubject of his legall remedy, for the recoverie of any goods, chattels, or rents, unlawfully taken or detayned from him. But for ſuch-meane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, Cuſtomes, prizes, and Rents, which have accrued unto his Majeſty ſince the 23 of Octob. 1641. except the Cuſtomes received at <hi>VVater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Roſſe</hi> ſince the 15. of <hi>September</hi> 1643. His majeſtie is content to remit the ſame, the reſt of the propoſition is anſwered in the anſwer to the fourth propoſition.</p>
            <p n="17">17. To the ſeventeenth, his Maieſty will be pleaſed, that ſuch perſons as ſhall bee excepted out of the generall pardon ſhalbe tryed by the knowne Lawes of this Land.</p>
            <p>The Lord marques of <hi>Ormond</hi> now declares that albeit theſe anſwers are thus given by him in preſent to the ſaid propoſitions, yet that hee intends not to be thereby concluded, from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the ſame, or adding thereunto in any parts there of, In ſuch ſort as he ſhall finde cauſe upon further debate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons_for_propositions">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104672:23"/>
            <head>Some of the reaſons which moved His Maiesties moſt humble and loyall Subiects the Confederate Roman Catholicks of Ireland to preſent certaine Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to His Excellencie the Lord Marques of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, His Maiesties Commiſsioner.</head>
            <p>THe firſt Propoſition that concerneth the freedome of the Catholicke Religion, and the repeale of all Lawes made againſt the profeſſors of that Religion, is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, not in favour of any innovation, but for that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which the Inhabitants of this Kingdome anciently, and like wiſe the Engliſh Colonies come at firſt into this Land, and their heires for many deſcents have profeſſed, and doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe at the preſent, and which before the raigne of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the <hi>VIII.</hi> was profeſſed by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and their ſubiects generally. And it may be further added, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirmed, that there are no ſubiects in the world of what other beleefe or profeſſion ſoever in Religion, that held themſelves ſo inviolably tyed to the preſervation of that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, to whom they owe ſubjection, and allegeance, as the profeſſors of the ſaid Roman Catholicke Religion.</p>
            <p>This propoſition conſiſteth of two branches, the firſt for the repeale of certaine acts, the ſecond that the freedome of their Religion may bee allowed to the ſaid Catholickes. For the cleering of the firſt branch, the ſaid Catholickes doe not preſſe the totall repeale of the ſaid ſtatutes, their humble requeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the great penalties, preſſures, incapacities, and other unavoidable inconveniences by the ſaid ſtatutes impoſed on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104672:24"/> them alone, may be removed as to them by act of Parliament. By one ſtatute found among the Records of Parliament of this kingdome in the ſecond yeare of the raigne of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. the ſaid Catholickes are made ſubiect to the arbitrary power of an high Commiſſion Court, or other Commiſſioners to be appointed by his Maieſty, or the Lord Deputie for the time being, &amp; may be queſtioned, &amp; puniſhed for all offences touching Religion. <hi>Irish ſtatutes fol.</hi> 261. like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>fol.</hi> 270. and 271. the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of another Religion have heavily puniſhed, and may ſtill puniſh the ſaid Catholickes for Marriages, Chriſtenings done according to the Catholicke Religion, and every Catholicke was driven to pay nine pence every Sunday for not repayring to Church, to the great impoveriſhment and deſtruction of the ſaid Catholickes, and no profit at all to his Maieſty.</p>
            <p>By the ſaid ſtatute, <hi>fol.</hi> 261. and 262. not onely the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Clergie, are excluded from all dignities &amp; benefices Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, but likewiſe the Catholicke Laytie of all degrees and qualities, are rendred incapable of all Civill offices, from the higheſt judge to the petty Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtable, &amp; likewiſe from Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall offices or imployments, even to be a common Souldier in his Maieſties army, where any fee or wages are due, without firſt taking the oath of ſupremacie; &amp; upon refuſall of the ſaid oath all dignities, offices, or wages are forfeyted.</p>
            <p>No Catholicke can ſue <hi>Livery</hi> or <hi>Ouſter le maine</hi> for his eſtate or any part thereof out of his Maieſties hands without taking the ſaid oath by the ſame ſtatute of 2 <hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 1 <hi>fol.</hi> 265. <hi>a.</hi> If any Catholicke of what eſtate, degree, or qualitie ſoever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this kingdome doe by writing, printing, teaching, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, expreſſe words, deede or act, affirme, hold, ſtand with, ſet forth, and maintayne any other authority, preheminence, power, or iuriſdiction in matters Eccleſiaſticall or Spirituall, then the perſon ſo offending his abbettors, ayders, promovers, and counſellers, ſhall for the firſt offence, forfeyte their goods and Leaſes, and ſuffer impriſonment for one yeare, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond offence incurre the paines and forfeytures ſet downe by the ſtatutes of <hi>Proviſion</hi> and <hi>Praemunire</hi> whereby the offender is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104672:24"/> put out of the Kings protection, impriſoned during his life, and his goods and lands forfeyted: For the third offence the offender is puniſhable as in caſe of high Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Then by conſequence if any of the Catholicke Laytie take or procure a diſpenſation for mariage within the eight degree, or any other licence or diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſation from any authoriſed by the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> is a principall offender, and if he heares the Maſſe or Sermon of any deriving power from thence, and keep him in his houſe, he is puniſhable as an ayder and abbettor within the words of the ſtatute, he knowing that whereof he cannot be ignorant by the rules of his profeſſion.</p>
            <p>As for the ſecond branch of the ſaid propoſition let any man iudge, whether it be reaſon ſufficient of it ſelfe, that the profeſſors of the Roman Catholicke Religion both ſpirituall and temporall, being to a few the Natives and reſidents of this kingdome ſhould deſire a freedome of their Religion, and to be freed and exempted from the penalties, and preſſures afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, whereby his Maieſty never received any advantage, and have beene the occaſion of many inconveniences in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>And it is evident that by this freedome all his Maieſties good ſubiects aſwell Proteſtants as Catholickes will bee uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more then ever before, when their condition is equall, and neyther partie have occaſion to envy or oppreſſe the other.</p>
            <p>It will not be unworthy of conſideration, that in reaſon of ſtate (the conſtitution of his Maieſties three kingdomes as now they ſtand being duely weighed) that this freedome, and exemption is moſt neceſſarie for his Maieſties ſervice and ſafetie.</p>
            <p>2. It is of the eſſence of Parliaments to be free, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was practiſed here; The compoſition of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is deſired to be of men eſtated and intereſted in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of genuyne and right members, and to bee returned from proper places, and by right miniſters.</p>
            <p>The ſuſpenſion of the act for this free Parliament cannot preiudice his Maieſty, for that nothing is to paſſe as an act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tranſmiſſion, other then what ſhall bee agreed upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104672:25"/> and expreſly mentioned in the Articles of peace.</p>
            <p>3. It is conceived this pretended Parliament was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the death of the Lord Deputy <hi>VVandesford,</hi> moſt of the eſtated and right members thereof did not appeare in it ſince the 7. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1641. thoſe who now appeare as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof <hi>viz.</hi> of the Commons-houſe, are for a great part not much intereſſed and other wholy unintereſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and one order therein made to exclude the ſaid Catholicks from the houſe, other orders to their diſadvantage were and or might have beene made in the ſaid Commons-houſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is deſired that all the proceedings of the ſaid pretended Parliament may be declared voyde and taken of the file.</p>
            <p>4. When thoſe indictments were found &amp; outlawries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulged, the ſaid Catholickes are informed, and hope to iuſtifie that thoſe who governed in this kingdome, or ſome of them, did plot and practiſe the totall extirpation of the ſaid Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, &amp; aſmuch as in them lay did encreaſe the troubles to that end, and ſhute up the gates of his Maieſties mercie againſt the ſaid catholickes, even againſt thoſe who were undeniably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, as may appeare by many inſtances; the manner of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of Sheriffes, who returned the Iurors, &amp; the perſons appointed, the Iurors condition &amp; affection, the infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the perſons indicted &amp; outlawed, being never called to anſwer, &amp; other circumſtances touching or depending of the ſaid Records, being ſo generally deſtructive to the ſaid Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks they cannot otherwiſe chooſe then to inſiſt on the taking them of from the file, that no ſuch markes of infamy may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne of Record, againſt them whoſe anceſtors for the ſpace of foure hundred yeares and upwards, faithfully ſerved the Crowne.</p>
            <p>5. This propoſition is ſo juſt and equall in it ſelfe, that there needeth not any reaſon or proofe to be urged for it.</p>
            <p>6. This propoſition being yeelded into by the anſwer, except the late Plantations in the County of <hi>VVicklow</hi> and <hi>Iduogh</hi> in the county of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> and excepting the encreaſe of Rents is referred to what ſhall bee urged upon the fixt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104672:25"/>
            <p> 7. In all or moſt Letters-patents granted of Plantation Lands, and ſome other lands in this kingdome ſince the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid ſtatutes, certaine clauſes and conditions were inſerted in them, that no land ſhould be ſold or paſt to any of the meere Iriſh or of the Iriſh Nation, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition is in ſome Patents, theſe clauſes doe &amp; did nouriſh diviſion and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between his Maieſties ſubiects, the like was never uſed in <hi>England,</hi> nor in any other kingdome. They extend not only to the old Iriſh, but likewiſe by conſtruction to the old Engliſh, for he that is borne in <hi>Ireland,</hi> though his parents and all his anceſtors were Aliens, nay if his parents were <hi>Indians</hi> or <hi>Turks</hi> if converted to Chriſtianitie is an Iriſh-man as fully, as if his anceſtors were here borne for thouſands of yeares, and by the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> as capable of the liberties of a ſubiect, Such markes of diſtinction being the inſteps to trouble and warre are incompatible with peace and quiet.</p>
            <p>8. The ſaid Roman Catholickes being rendred incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any command or truſt by the ſtatutes aforeſaid, may be relieved herein upon removall of the impediments mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the reaſons for the firſt propoſition, and particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhewed for the preſent, yet ſuch were the Character, layed upon them here, and the repreſentations made of them from hence heretofore into <hi>England,</hi> that they apprehend they ſuffer thereby in his Majeſties opinion of them, which they conceive an impediment and ſtop to many graces and favours they expect and hope to merite from his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>In all ages paſt before the ſaid ſtatutes their anceſtors were preferred to places of eminence and truſt within their Native countries, and ſince very ſeldome, three preſidents ſince can hardly be inſtanced.</p>
            <p>The condition of Roman Catholickes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where there are an hundred Catholickes to one of any other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on differs much from that of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> where there is ſcarce one Catholicke to a thouſand of the proteſtant religion.</p>
            <p>In all the Nations of Chriſtendome the Natives of the place are advanced before others.</p>
            <p>9. The Court of Wards was begun here a bout the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104672:26"/> yeare of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and never before: It hath not the warrant of any Law or ſtatute; In <hi>England</hi> it was erected by act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The ſubject is extreamely oppreſſed thereby by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of informations againſt all freeholders from the higheſt to the loweſt without any limitation of time, the frequent Courts of <hi>Eſcheaters</hi> &amp; <hi>Feodaries,</hi> the deſtruction of the <hi>Tenures</hi> of meſnes Lords by making many Tenures to be <hi>In Capite</hi> againſt Law; by the ſale of the wards from hand to hand, as of Horſes in a Market, by the want of Proviſion for portions of younger children, whereby they periſh or take ill courſes; debts remaine unſatisfied, and though by the ſtatute of <hi>Merton cap.</hi> 5. Vſurie doth not runne upon Infants, yet the Collaterall ſecurity ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of men or Land mortgaged are not relieved by that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
            <p>The King never received one ſhilling advantage by this Court <hi>ultra repriſas,</hi> for twenty ſhillings damage done thereby to his people, the vaſt fortunes of the officers and miniſters of the ſaid Court, how ſuddainely rayſed on the ruynes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others his Majeſties ſubjects. And let all the wards ſince the erection of the Court be numbred, for one that gayned civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or breeding during their minority, many will be found to have departed the ſaid Court with ignorance, loſſe or impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their eſtates and other great inconveniences.</p>
            <p>No diminution of his Majeſties profit is deſired, the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſervice upon all occaſions ſhall be performed. The extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this Court and of the Tenures <hi>in capite</hi> or by Knights ſervice is humbly deſired to be taken away, and a courſe for his Majeſties profit and ſervice and preſervation of Heires and Orphans, and ſatisfaction of Creditors ſhall be then humbly propoſed.</p>
            <p>The reſpit and iſſues of homage being of no conſiderable advantage to the Crowne, and an intolerable yoke to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is likewiſe deſired to be taken off, and a way of equall benefit to his Majeſty ſhall be propoſed.</p>
            <p>10. The great number of theſe Lords unintereſſed in the kingdome, their ends in ſeeking for thoſe honours, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:104672:26"/> late introduction of the example being conſidered; it may be eaſily judged how unequall or unjuſt it is that the votes of men of no eſtate and never reſident in the kingdome if not for deſigne, ſhould impoſe a charge wherein they contribute nothing, or put Lawes, by which they are not bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>11. The independencie of the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> is ſo cleere and manifeſt by Law, Iuſtice, uſage, and neceſſitie, that they humbly deſire it may not bee driven into diſpute, yet in as much as the Royall aſſent wreſted from his Majeſtie to the acts of ſubſcription may draw a preiudice or diſcountenance upon our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a declaration herein and act of Parliament is deſired.</p>
            <p>12. This propoſition is in it ſelfe ſo reaſonable, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint layed on the Councell-Table from taking cognizance of matters determinable in the Kings ordinarie courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice by the Common Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the great Charter thirty times confirmed by Parliament, and ſundry other acts of Parliament of force in this Kingdome, is ſo manifeſt and cleere, that there is no need of further reaſoning or proofe for the ſame; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is conſonant to Law &amp; Iuſtice, that the partyes aggree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhould bee reſtored to what they loſt, and left in <hi>ſtatu quo, &amp;c.</hi> as is deſired, and that no matter determinable in the ordinarie Courts may bee determined at the Councell-table.</p>
            <p>13. This propoſition being for free trade and commerce ſo neceſſarie for advancement of his Maieſties ſervice and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and ſo indifferently inducing to the weale of his people, it is conceived, that all who are intereſſed in the Kingdome, ought to contribute their endeavours for the attaining of what is thereby humbly deſired.</p>
            <p>14. The place of chiefe governour of this Kingdome being of ſo great honour and high truſt, and therfore to be conferred upon ſuch as ſtudie his Maieſties ſervice, and the proſperitie of the Kingdome without regard to particular intereſt; this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation will keepe the chiefe governor warie from offending any ſubiect, or deſcending ſo low as to give occaſion, even of ſpeech, that his actions are unwarrantable, or his purchaſes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104672:27"/> by oppreſſion, men are to bee choſen for this place, that have no need to purchaſe.</p>
            <p>15. The malice and power of the malignant partie in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Scotland, and of their adherents abroad, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned danger of in vaſion to bee made by them, and the invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereunto of many in this Kingdome, who are knowne to have ſtudied and plotted the ruine of this Kingdome, are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ſufficient for the granting of the contents of this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that the Kingdome be alwayes in poſture of defence of it ſelfe, and all the well affected ſubiects thereof.</p>
            <p>16. The paſſing of an act of oblivion to quiet and ſecure the mindes of all his Maieſties ſubiects in a caſe ſo generall, wherein the moſt of his Maieſties ſubiects one way or other are involved, is ſo neceſſary, and ſo purſuing the preſidents, and examples, not onely of England and Ireland, but alſo of other States and Kingdomes, that without the paſſing thereof ſome Imbers of miſchiefe may ſtill remaine, which may (though God forbid) turne unto great flammes, witneſſe the <hi>Barons warres,</hi> the warres of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> theſe preſent troubles of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other examples, even in this Kingdome. And it there be any poſſibilitie to relieve all particulars, when the generall concernment is in queſtion.</p>
            <p>17. Honour, Iuſtice, equitie, and reaſon of State doe pleade for this propoſition.</p>
            <p>Wee deſire notwithſtanding thoſe reaſons to bee admitted to ſhew ſuch further and other reaſons, and adde hereunto what wee ſhall thinke fit touching the matters, wherein the anſwers are ſhort, or not ſatisfactorie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:104672:27"/>
            <p>As the Lord Lieutenant in his anſwer gave the Propoſers no occaſion to uſe any unfitting expreſſions, ſo hee may not but declare the Compariſon, and ſome other expreſſions in their preamble, to bee very unneceſſary, and unſeaſonable, and ſuch as hee may not admit however hee now offereth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation_of_response">
            <head>An Explanation of ſome of the anſwers given by IAMES Marques of Ormond His Majesties Commiſsioner, for the concluding of a Peace in this Kingdome to the Propoſitions of His Maieſties Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicke ſubiects of Ireland with ſome further Conceſsions.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw.</hi> FOr the exception taken to the anſwer to the firſt Propoſition, although neyther the ſtatute of 2. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1. nor any other ſtatute of force in this kingdome doe impoſe any mulct or penalty for ſaying, ſinging, or hearing Maſſe, or keeping a Roman Catholicke prieſt in their houſes, yet his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty for the further ſatisfaction of his ſaid Roman Catholicke ſubjects, in any doubt or ſcruple, that may ariſe upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of any of the ſaid ſtatutes which may diſquiet their mindes, is graciouſly pleaſed that a declaration of the law as unto that point be prepared and publiſhed. And his Majeſty is likewiſe graciouſly pleaſed to ſuſpend the high Commiſſion Court: And that as the oath of ſupremacie hath not beene impoſed upon any of them of late times upon the ſuing of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries,</hi> ſo they ſhall for the time to come be admitted to ſue their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104672:28"/> 
               <hi>Liveries</hi> upon taking the oath by his Majeſties directions in that caſe provided, which being added to the anſwers to the eight propoſition (by which his Majeſty hath declared that they ſhall receive ſuch markes of his favour in offices and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of truſt as ſhall manifeſt his Majeſties good acceptance and regarde of them) may for the preſent aboundantly ſatisfie his ſaid ſubjects, And for the repeale of any of the acts intended by the ſaid propoſition his Majeſtie will further adviſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the exception taken to the word new Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the anſwer to the ſecond propoſition, Whereas a free Parliament was propounded, The ſaid Lord Marqueſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that the ſaid new Parliament is to bee as free, as by the lawes and ſtatutes of this kingdome any parliament to bee held in this kingdome ought to be, yet ſo as no interpretation be from thence made, that there ſhould bee any proceeding in the ſaid parliament in any particular contrary to the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on this Treatie. As to the exception taken to the clauſe in the anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> that the parliament ſhall be diſſolved upon an attempt onely of propounding any other matter then ſhall be agreed upon by the articles of peace, albeit the clauſe is not ſo as it is recited, Yet the Lord Marqueſſe for their further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is pleaſed that the word attempt be left out of the clauſe wherein it is, and it bee expreſſed in manner following <hi>viz.</hi> And that nothing be concluded by both or eyther of the ſaid houſes of parliament, which may bring prejudice to any of his Majeſties proteſtant partie or their adherents.</p>
            <p>And for their deſire to have <hi>Poynings</hi> act ſuſpended, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is aſſented unto, that no act of parliament is to paſſe upon the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Poynings</hi> act without tranſmiſſion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the uſuall manner, but what ſhall be provided for in the Articles of peace, And that it is enacted by act of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of force in this kingdome, that <hi>Poynings</hi> act cannot bee ſuſpended, but by Bill to be firſt agreed upon by both houſes of parliament in this kingdome, which is likewiſe to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted according to the uſuall manner, which will take up aſmuch time as the tranſmitting of the Bils which are to bee agreed on this Treaty, And ſeeing the benefits which ſhall be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104672:28"/> held fit to be derived to the propoſers may be as effectually, and with more ſpeed done without ſuſpending of <hi>Poynings</hi> act, as by ſuſpending thereof; His Majeſtie doth not ſee cauſe why the ſame ſhould be deſired, But he is very apprehenſive of the prejudice the ſuſpenſion thereof may bring upon himſelfe, and the publicke ſervice by diſquieting the mindes of his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubjects in both kingdomes, if that he ſhould admit ſuch innovation at this time, there being no neceſſitie thereof, and therefore his Majeſtie aſwell for that as other weighty conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, may not vary as unto that particular from his former anſwer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If both or eyther of the houſes of parliament have made any orders wherein his Majeſties concurrence hath not beene, It doth reſt onely in the power of the houſe or houſes and not in his Majeſtie to vacate ſuch orders, except they doe appeare in themſelves to be illegall, And in ſuch caſes his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will declare ſuch to be voyde, and give directions for the vacating of them as in the particular whereof inſtance is made, for excluding members duely elected and returned according to the eſtabliſhed lawes of this kingdome out of the houſe of Commons, who ſhould refuſe to take the oath of ſupremacie, which without an act of parliament to warrant it cannot bee in ſuch caſe impoſed, but his Majeſtie may not admit the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament to be voyde, nor declare all that hath beene done therein ſince the ſeventh of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1641. to bee voyde for that many orders much tending to his Majeſties honour and the ſafetie of this kingdome, wherein both houſes did joyne have beene made ſince that time, as the prohibiting the taking of the Covenant ſo deſtructive to Monarchy, and the Church, which hath been condemned by both the ſaid houſes, Their joynt approbation of the late Ceſſation, The petition wherein both houſes joyned to his Majeſtie, and others of that kinde.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Touching the exception taken to that part of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the fourth propoſition concerning the Generall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, The Lord Marqueſſe declares that it is meant thereby that the ſaid generall pardon ſhall extend to reſtore them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104672:29"/> ſuch as ſhall be on this Treaty agreed to be excepted, to their bloud and eſtate by act of parliament, whereby all Grantes, Letters-patents, Acts, Letters, Promiſes ſhall bee avoyded. But his Majeſtie cannot in juſtice publiſh any ſuch Proclamation, or give any ſuch direction to the parliament as is deſired, before the perſons intended to be charged be heard, and the matters ſuggeſted proved, which if they ſhall, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will then doe therein what ſhall be juſt. And in the meane time cannot thinke ill of his miniſters of ſtate imployed in this kingdome, nor of the proceedings of any of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Courts of Iuſtice, And for their deſire that there ſhould be no exception in the pardon, his Majeſtie may not aſſent thereunto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Majeſtie will be pleaſed that debts doe ſtand <hi>in statu quo,</hi> having as unto ſuch who ſhalbe agreed in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be excepted out of the generall pardon, and excepting one particular ſumme which hath beene payed into his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Exchequer.</p>
            <p n="6">6. His Majeſty may not agree to the avoyding of the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the countie of <hi>VVicklow,</hi> &amp; Territory of <hi>Idough</hi> in the countie of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> part of the Lands in the countie of <hi>VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> viz. the <hi>Ranelagh</hi> being confirmed by act of parliament, and ſo much of the reſt of the lands in the ſaid county as fell to his Majeſtie upon the diviſion, and the Territory of <hi>Idough</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed by Letters-patents under the great Seale upon the Commiſſion of Grace for remedy of defective Titles, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned likewiſe by act of Parliament, which his Majeſtie may not in honour avoyde, And his Majeſtie doth conceive it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe for divers of his Majeſties ſubjects, who have purchaſed, eſtates grounded upon his Majeſties title, that the ſtatute of Limitations ſhould have ſuch a retroſpect as is deſired, which in time would overthrow the eſtates of many of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſubjects, who acquired eſtates for valuable conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, And therefore his Majeſtie may not aſſent thereunto, but for taking off or abating of Rents contracted or agreed for, his Majeſtie is pleaſed that the courſe preſcribed in his anſwer to the twelfth additionall propoſition be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104672:29"/> 7. His Majeſtie may not admit that the governing of the Innes of Court, Vniverſitie, and free-ſchooles by ſuch ſtatutes rules and orders, as his Majeſtie ſhall approve of, and be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the cuſtomes of <hi>England</hi> will debarre Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes ſo long as they are of that Religion from attayning to the lawes of the Land, or any other learning within the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for thoſe of that Religion in <hi>England,</hi> and who goe from hence doe attayne the knowledge of both in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and Innes of Court there in an eminent manner, and may doe the like here.</p>
            <p n="8">8. There being no offices or place excepted in the former anſwer, the Propoſers may reſt ſatisfied therewith, it being in his Majeſties power to diſpoſe of ſuch places and offices by his Letters-patents as occaſion ſhall be offered, and thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all impediments mentioned by the Propoſers.</p>
            <p n="9">9. His Majeſtie doth not admit ſuch abuſes to have beene in his Court of wards and the miniſters thereof, as are ſet forth in the reaſons for the ninth propoſition, untill proofe bee made thereof, And his Maieſtie doth beleeve that exceeding great benefit may redound to the kingdome, by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and right ordering thereof, And therefore conceiveth his former anſwer to be reaſonable, And it ſeemeth not equall which is propounded that there ſhould bee firſt an extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the Court, and the Tenures <hi>in capite</hi> taken away, and that then a courſe for his Maieſties profit and ſervice ſhould be propoſed, that being to be offered in the firſt place before his Maieſtie part with the other, And the like is to be done for reſpit of homage.</p>
            <p n="10">10. His Maieſtie may not receade from the former anſwer with which the Propoſers may reſt ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As his Maieſtie may not vary from his former anſwer, ſo he may not forecloſe the houſes of parliament from making any declaration agreeable to the lawes of the land.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The Propoſers may reſt ſatisfied with the former anſwer, conſidering that all parties grieved may have the benefit of the lawes of the land, and that by conſent of the parties intereſted many matters determined at Councell-board are confirmed by act of parliament.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104672:30"/> 13. His Maieſtie will be pleaſed that indifferent perſons be agreed on this treatie who ſhall be authoriſed by Commiſſion to moderate and ſettle the Booke of Rates in ſuch ſorre as they ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p n="14">14. His Maieſtie may not aſſent any further to this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then he hath already done without apparent preiudice to his ſervice.</p>
            <p n="15">15. His Maieſtie may not receade from his former anſwer.</p>
            <p n="16">16. His Maieſtie thinkes not fit to give any further anſwer to this Propoſition then he hath done already, untill the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers make anſwer to the propoſitions made and delivered unto them in the behalfe of his Maieſties proteſtant ſubiects and their adherents. And then upon further debate his Maieſtie will give ſuch anſwer as ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p n="17">17. It may not be admitted that tryals by the knowne lawes of the land aſſented unto by the former anſwer ſhould not be indifferent, And therefore his Maieſtie may not receade from his former anſwer:</p>
            <p>The ſaid Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> now declares, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit theſe anſwers are thus given by him in preſent to the ſaid propoſitions, yet that he intends not to be thereby concluded from altering the ſame or adding thereunto in any parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in ſuch ſorte as he ſhall finde cauſe upon further debate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="additional_propositions">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104672:30"/>
            <head>Additionall Propoſitions of His Majeſties moſt humble and loyall ſubjects the Confederate Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks of Ireland, preſented to His Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the Lord Marques of Ormond; Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of Ireland, His Majeſties Commiſsioner.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat an act bee paſſed this next Parliament, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that neither the Lord Deputie, Lord Chancellor, Lord High Treaſurer, Vice-Treaſurer, Chancellor, or any of the Barrons of the Erchequer, privy councell, or Iudges of the foure Courts bee Farmers of his Majeſties Cuſtomes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That an act of Parliament may paſſe in this Kingdome againſt all Monopolies, ſuch as was enacted in England, 21. <hi>Iacobi,</hi> with a further clauſe for repealing of all grants of monopolies in this Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Court of Caſtle-chamber in this Kingdome, having been an oppreſſion to the ſubject, &amp; there being other remedies for the offences queſtioned in that Court by the Common Law and Statutes of the Realme, be taken away, or otherwiſe limitted, as both houſes of Parliament ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That two acts lately paſt in this Kingdome, one prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the plowing with horſes by the taile, and the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the burning of oates in ſtraw may bee repealed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That upon preſenting the names of three perſons of qualitie in each Countie by Vs to your Lordſhip, patents be paſſed to ſuch of thoſe ſo to bee preſented reſpectively to be Sheriffs in each County, as to your Lordſhip ſhall ſeeme meet to make choice of for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104672:31"/> 6. That one, or more Agents from this Kingdome, may bee admitted ſtill to attend his Majeſtie for his better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the affaires of this Kingdome; And that as a teſtimony of his Majeſties favour, ſome of the nobles and others of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Kingdome may be imployed about his Majeſties perſon.</p>
            <p n="7">7. For aſmuch as divers of the Scottiſh Nation, and others in this Kingdome doe not obey the preſent ceſſation, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them having of late taken the Covenant propoſed by the members of Parliament at Weſtminſter now in armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſtie. It is therefore humbly deſired that ſuch as diſobey the ſaid Ceſſation, or have taken the ſaid Covenant, bee proclaimed traytors, and proſecuted accordingly by his Majeſties authoritie, and that ſuch Counties or Corporations as have not ſubmitted to the now Ceſſation of armes in this Kingdome, according his Maieſties Commiſſion, be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to make any returne to the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">8. For aſmuch as ſundry perſons eſtated in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, have either actually raiſed armes in England, againſt his Majeſtie, or have otherwiſe adhered to the malignant partie now in armes againſt his Majeſtie, that therefore it may pleaſe his Majeſtie to give way to the impeachment and attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of thoſe, and ſuch others whoſe names we ſhall here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to your Lordſhip by way of bill in Parliament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may receive condigne puniſhment for their offences, &amp; his Majeſty take advantage of the forfeiture of their eſtates, and in the interim the poſſeſſions to remaine in the hands wherein they are at preſent.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For aſmuch as upon application of the Agents from this Kingdome to his Majeſtie, in the fourth yeare of his raigne, and lately upon humble ſuite made to his Majeſtie, by a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of both houſes of the Parliament of this Kingdome, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was given by his Majeſtie for redreſſe of ſeverall gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances; It is therefore humbly deſired, that for ſo many of thoſe as are not expreſſed in the now propoſitions preſented to your Lordſhip, whereof both houſes in the next enſuing Parliament, ſhall deſire the benefit of his Majeſties ſaid former
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104672:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> directions for redreſſes that the ſame bee afforded them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That the office of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in this Kingdome bee ſetled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dependant of none but his Majeſtie, whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritime cauſes may bee determined here without driving mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or others, to appeale or ſeeke Iuſtice elſewhere in thoſe cauſes.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That a Courſe may be taken for all ſuch as owe debts in this Kingdome for that by reaſon of the generall devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kingdome, the land is not like in ſome yeares to come to be of any conſiderable value, being the onely meanes that many of the Nobilitie, Gentrie, and others of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had to ſatisfie their debts, and therefore a competent time bee given by act to bee paſt in the next Parliament for payment thereof and the intereſt or uſe of moneyes to bee moderated.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That the ſubjects of this Kingdome may bee eaſed of the increaſe of rent lately rayſed and impoſed on them upon the late Commiſſion of defective titles in the Earle of Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords time.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That if any of your Lordſhips partie during theſe troubles, have by fines, recoveries or otherwiſe diſinherited thoſe who were next to ſucceed them of our partie as heires, or in reverſion, or remainder without reall and full conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but for being of our partie, that all acts ſo done be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Parliament.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That ſuch of our partie whoſe eſtates are in the hands of the Scottiſh and Parliament partie, either in this Kingdome or in England, bee recompenced out of the eſtates of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant in this Kingdome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_additional_propositions">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:104672:32"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of IAMES Marques of Ormond, his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioner, for the treatie and concluding of a Peace in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for and in the Name, and behalfe, of his Majeſtie, to the additionall Propoſitions of his Roman Catholicke ſubjects of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhen all the particular demands made on the behalfe of his Majeſtie, the Church, and his Majesties Proteſtant ſubjects, and their partie, shall bee concluded his Majestie will be graciouſly pleaſed on his part, to agree to the particulars hereafter expreſſed, viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. TO the firſt propoſition, his Maieſtie hath declared his pleaſure in this point (excepting in that part which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes privie Counſellors) in his anſwer to the eight grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in the ſeventeenth yeare of his Maieſties raigne, which his Maieſtie will be graciouſly pleaſed may ſtand as a rule in this caſe, And as to that part which concernes privie Counſellors, the ſame ſhall be humbly repreſented to his Maieſtie and his Royall pleaſure therein expected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the ſecond propoſition, his Maieſtie will be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to aſſent to this propoſition yet ſo as firſt there be care taken to ſecure his Maieſty in the particulars propoſed in the ſixt, and ſeventh Articles of the demands in the behalfe of his Maieſtie delivered by the Lord Lieutenant on this treatie to the Lord <hi>Muskery,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the third propoſition, The particulars wherein it is deſired, that the Court of Caſtle-chamber may be limitted, are to be propoſed, and then ſuch conſideration ſhall bee had of this propoſition as ſhall be fit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the fourth propoſition, his Maieſty will be graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly pleaſed, that the two acts in this propoſition mentioned be ſuſpended for ſuch time, as on this treaty ſhal be agreed on.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To the fift propoſition, The lawes have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the manner of appointing Sheriffes, from which courſe his Maieſtie thinkes not fit to vary.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:104672:32"/> 6. To the ſixt propoſition, After a peace ſhall be fully ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, application may be had herein to his Maieſtie, who in his high wiſedome beſt knowes how to extend his Royall favour in this particular.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To the ſeventh propoſition, For the firſt part of this propoſition, the Lord Lieutenant declareth that his Maieſties Commiſſion to him warranting this treaty, gives him autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to conclude a Peace, but gives him no authority for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſhing ſuch a Proclamation, or for ſuch a proſecution, as in this propoſition is propoſed, and for the later part of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition the granting thereof is inconſiſtent with the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a free parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To the eight propoſition, when the Propoſers ſhall preſent to the Lord Lieutenant the names of the perſons in this propoſition intended to be impeached and attaynted, ſuch conſideration ſhalbe had of this propoſition as ſhalbe fit.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To the ninth propoſition, the propoſers ſetting downe the particulars of the things contayned in this propoſition, ſuch conſideration ſhall be had thereof as ſhalbe fit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. To the tenth propoſition, his Maieſty will be pleaſed to adviſe concerning this propoſition.</p>
            <p n="11">11. To the eleventh propoſition, this is left to further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration on debate.</p>
            <p n="12">12. To the twelfth propoſition, this is not held fit for his Maieſty to be aſſented to on this treaty, yet the caſe of remittals or abatements we intend humbly to repreſent to his Maieſtie, who will be graciouſly pleaſed in fit time to ſet downe ſuch a courſe herein by Commiſſion or otherwiſe, as may ſtill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther magnify his goodneſſe and indulgence to all his ſubiects.</p>
            <p n="13">13 To the thirteenth propoſition, his Maieſty may not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this, it being againſt the libertie of the ſubiect, and the lawes of the Land.</p>
            <p n="14">14. To the fourteenth propoſition, Such of the eſtates in this propoſition mentioned, as ſhall a crue to his Maieſty is to be left to his Maieſty to be diſpoſed of as in his high wiſedome he ſhall thinke fit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="demands">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104672:33"/>
            <head>Demands in the behalfe of His Maieſtie,</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat preſent reſtitution bee made by the Confederate Roman Catholicke Party. of the Command, Rule and Government of the Cities of <hi>Limmericke, VVaterford, Kilkenny</hi> and <hi>Cashell,</hi> the Townes of <hi>Galway, Clonmell, VVeixford,</hi> and <hi>Roſſe,</hi> and of all other Cities, Townes, Counties, and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of right belonging to his Majeſty, and now in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or under the command of the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, &amp; that reſtitution be like wiſe made by them of all his Maieſties Caſtles, Fortes, Lands, Tenements, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments, and of all his Maieſties Ordnance, Artillerie, Armes, and Amunition, which have beene ſeiſed on, or taken by the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, ſince the 21. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. in the Cities of <hi>Limmericke, VVaterford, Galway,</hi> the Caſtle and Towne of <hi>Newry, Charlemount,</hi> and other places within the kingdome, And that all ſuch power, Iuriſdiction or Government as hath beene aſſumed by the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party over their partie, ſince the 22. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. be from hence forth abrogated deſerted and deemed voyde, And that all his Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects aſwell the Roman Catholickes as others within the kingdome ſhall be from henceforth ameaneable to the Lawes of force in this kingdome, and obedient to his Maieſties go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Courts of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all the Armies rayſed by the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, with their Armes and munition, and ſuch Fortes, Garriſons and Wardes, as are now kept by them, ſhall from henceforth be under the command of his Maieſtie, and his Maieſties Lieutenant, or other his Maieſties chiefe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor or governors of this kingdome for the time being, and ſuch others, as his Maieſty from time to time ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:104672:33"/> 3. Thirdly, that his Maieſty may be anſwered ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Rents, Compoſitions and Caſuall profits and Subſidies, and all Cuſtomes, and Subſidies for Merchandize as were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crued and growne due before and on the 23. of <hi>October</hi> 1641 and which ſhall from henceforth grow due.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That all the remaine of the thirty thouſand eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound appearing to be payable to his Maieſtie by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument ſigned by the Lord <hi>Muskery</hi> and others, dated 16. of <hi>September</hi> 1643. which hath not yet beene payed in money or Cattle, in manner as in an Inſtrument ſigned by the ſaid Lord <hi>Muskery</hi> and others, dated the xvj. of <hi>September</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred forty and three, is expreſled, bee payed to his Maieſties Vice-treaſurer and Treaſurer at Wars, or to his deputy, or to ſuch other perſon or perſons as the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, or other chiefe governor or governors of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for the time being ſhall appoint, to his Maieſties uſe, by the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, at by or before the day of next</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke partie doe make a true account and preſent payment of his Maieſties Cuſtomes and Impoſitions of <hi>VVaterford</hi> and <hi>Roſſe,</hi> according to the Booke of Rates, for all ſuch Commodities as have been exported out of, or imported into the ſaid Harbours ſince the xv. of <hi>September</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the grant of the Licencing of retayling Wine and Aquavitae, and of tranſportation of Linnen-yarne at per packe in <hi>Ireland</hi> towards the ſupport of the charge of this kingdome, may be ſetled by act of Parliament upon the Crown, according to the reſolution in his Maieſties late graces in the yeare 1641. with ſome apt Proviſo, that they may be kept and continued as a Revenue to the Crowne.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That on the pound of Tobacco be ſetled by act of parliament unto his Maieſties uſe, as a Cuſtome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Commoditie, whereupon the emption of Tobacco to be free, and the Monopoly wholy taken away.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="demands">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:104672:34"/>
            <head>Demands in the behalfe of the Proteſtant Clergie.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and all other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons be preſently reſtored to their reſpective Churches, Iuriſdictions and poſſeſſions, both spirituall and Temporall, and to the free exerciſe of their ſeverall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective functions, and that they enjoy the ſame without any interruption to be given thereunto by the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, in ſuch manner as they have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, before and on the 23. of <hi>October</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all Cathedrall and pariſh Churches, and all Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Biſhops, Manſion-houſes, which have beene any way demoliſhed or defaced, by any of the ſaid Confederate Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicke party, ſhall be withall convenient ſpeede by the Confederate Roman Catholicke party repayted, and put in as good condition as they were on the 23. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That for the preſent ſubſiſtence of the proteſtant Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, they may be allowed the one halfe of all the Tythe Corne belonging to their benefices reſpectively aryſing out of this preſent Harveſt 1644. within the quarters allotted by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Ceſſation to the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, or the value thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="demands">
            <head>Demands in the behalfe of all His Maiesties Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubiects, and their Party.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat preſent reſtitution be made unto them of all their Caſtles, Lordſhips, Mannors, and all other Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Chattles reall, of what kinde ſoever, whereof they were ſeaſed or poſſeſſed by themſelves or their Tenants on the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:104672:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> 22. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. and which remayne within the quarters allotted by the Articles of Ceſſation to the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That where any of the goods, Evidences, or writings of the proteſtant ſubjects, and ſuch as adhere unto them, have beene delivered in truſt to any that are or have beene, of the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke party, to be kept by any of them, That ſuch goods, Evidences, and writings be reſtored to thoſe that ſo delivered them in truſt as aforeſaid, or to their heires, executors, adminiſtrators or aſſignes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all goods which have beene pillaged and taken away by any of the ſaid Confederate Roman Catholicke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which may be had <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> and the property whereof was not altered by ſale in market before the 24. day of <hi>Iune</hi> 1644. (being the day of the date of his Maieſties Commiſſion war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting this Treaty) be reſtored, or otherwiſe the Proprietor may be left to his remedy at Common-law for the recoverie thereof, and that any ſale in market ſince the ſaid 24. of <hi>Iune,</hi> ſhall be no hinderance or barre thereunto.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That where any of that party have pillaged or taken away any goods from any of his Maieſties proteſtant ſubiects, or any adhering to them, betweene the 21. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. and the 21. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1641. that the party ſo pillaged may be left to take his remedy at law for recovery of his goods or da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages for the ſame againſt ſuch who did ſo pillage them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That all Caſtles and houſes which were ſurrendred upon quarter, upon Articles under hands, wherein it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, that the ſaid Caſtles or houſes ſhould bee preſerved from being deſtroyed or demoliſhed, That the ſaid Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates who have ſo articled may rebuild the ſaid Caſtles or houſes, in as good ſtate as they were at the ſurrendring up of the ſame, upon Articles as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That where any Lands belonging to his Maieſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſubjects or their tenants or adherents have beene poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by any of the ſaid Confederate Roman catholicke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and corne ſowen therein by any of that party ſince the 15. of <hi>September</hi> 1643. that the ſaid proteſtant ſubjects or their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104672:35"/> adherents who by themſelves or their tenants were poſſeſſed of the ſaid Lands on the 22. of <hi>October</hi> 1641. or their Heires, Executors, Adminiſtrators, or Aſſignes may reſpectively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the fourth ſheafe of all the ſaid corne this preſent Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt 1644. or the value thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe propoſitions thus made in preſent are not in excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any other propoſitions which we ſhall adjudge neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be propounded or inſiſted on for the glory of God, the honour of his Maieſty, the intereſts of his good ſubjects, and the ſafety of the kingdome, nor in excluſion of ſundry other particulars which may be neceſſary for us to inſiſt on, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the formerly mentioned ends, and which may ariſe upon the preſent Treaty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_demands">
            <head>Anſwers to the demands made by the Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the behalfe of His Maiestie.</head>
            <p>1. TO the firſt Demand his Maieſties faithfull ſubiects the Confederate Catholickes of his kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> doe anſwer, that the Cities, and Townes in the ſaid demand men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, are, and alwayes have beene ruled, and governed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Maieſties Lawes, and the Charters unto them reſpectively granted by his Maieſty, and his Royall progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and predeceſſors Kings, and Queenes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and are preſerved and kept by the ſaid Confederate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes for his uſe, and ſervice againſt the malignant partie, and their adherents. And as for his Maieſties Fortes, Caſtles, Territories, Hereditaments, Ordnance and Artillery, in the ſame demand mentioned, the ſame are likewiſe kept, and maintayned for his Maieſties uſe and ſervice, and the ſafetie of the kingdome and his Maieſties intereſts therein againſt ſuch as are joyned in a rebellious covenant, and are actually in armes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104672:35"/> againſt his Royall perſon. And they know of no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amunition taken by the ſaid Catholickes, and ſuch as was ſo taken, and much more was by them imployed in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſervice, And as to the power and juriſdiction mentioned to be aſſumed by the ſaid Confederate catholickes, they ſay they were neceſſitated to rule and governe their party to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde the extirpation of their Religion and Nation plotted, and contrived by the ſaid malignant party, and to preſerve his Maieſties rights. And their proceedings were, and are as neere and conſonant to the lawes of the kingdome, as the ſtate and condition of the times did, or can permit. And they will bee ready to relinquiſh the ſaid rule, and government upon a full ſetlement of the affaires of the kingdome.</p>
            <p>2. To the ſecond they anſwer that the armies raiſed by the ſaid Confederate Catholickes were rayſed, and the ſaid armies Fortes, Garriſons and Wardes in the demand mentioned are maintayned for the ſafety of the kingdome, and to preſerve his Maieſties intereſts, and the ſaid armies alwayes were and are in actuall ſervice accordingly, and that upon a full ſetlement, the ſame are to be diſpoſed of as his Maieſty will direct.</p>
            <p>3. To the third they ſay that ſo much of the profits therein mentioned as grew dew ſince the ſeventh day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1641. (on which day happened that inforced and fatall adjourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the parliament from whence all the diſtractions of this kingdome did ſpring) as was received by the ſaid Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Catholickes, and many an hundred times more was by them imployed and expended in his Maieſties ſervice for the defence of the kingdome, And the ſaid profits for the time to come after a full ſetlement are to be diſpoſed by ſuch hands, as his Maieſtie ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p>4. To the fourth they ſay that the free gift granted to his Maieſtie by the ſaid Confederate Catholickes is already over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed, as ſhall be made appeare upon account by the ſupreme Counſell of the ſaid Confederate Catholickes, to whom that affaire is intruſted.</p>
            <p>5. To the fifth they ſay that the Portes of <hi>VVaterford</hi> and <hi>Roſse,</hi> being within the quarters of the ſaid Confederate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104672:36"/> by the Articles of Ceſſation, they have according the ſaid articles received the profits accruing out of the cuſtomes of thoſe portes, and imployed the ſame in his Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and defence of the kingdome.</p>
            <p>6. 7. The matters contayned in the ſixt and ſeventh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are properly to be determined in ſuch manner as ſhalbe agreed upon in the concluſion of this treatie. And what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concernes the ſaid demands, or the matters in them, or any of them contayned wee conceive proper for a debate &amp; to bee determined upon concluſion of the treaty.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Confederate Catholickes doe referre their anſwers to the demands made on the behalfe of the proteſtant Clergy to the firſt of the propoſitions preſented by them, And to the debate and determination thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_demands">
            <head>Anſwers to the Demands made on the behalfe of His Maiesties Proteſtant ſubjects:</head>
            <p>1. TO the firſt the ſaid Confederate Catholicks doe anſwer, that after a full ſetlement of affaires, reciprocall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is to be made aſwell to the ſaid Confederate Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes, and every of them, as alſo to his Maieſties ſaid proteſtant ſubiects, and to every of them, other then ſuch of the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants as are or ſhalbe joyned in a rebellious covenant againſt his Maieſty, or adhere to the malignant party of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Caſtles, Lordſhips, Mannors, hereditaments, and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels reall, whereof they were reſpectively ſeiſed or poſſeſſed on the 22. of <hi>October.</hi> 1641. within the quarters allotted to ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party by the articles of Ceſſation, And other then the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104672:36"/> Caſtles, Lordſhips, Mannors, and hereditaments in the county of <hi>VVicklow,</hi> and in the Territory of <hi>Idough,</hi> out of which the Natives thereof were by an high and injurious hand, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trajudiciall &amp; arbitrary proceedings expulſed ſince the yeare of our Lord God 1633.</p>
            <p>2. 3. 4. To the ſecond, third, and fourth, they ſay that the ſaid Confederate Catholickes are much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mnified therein then the ſaid proteſtants. And yet in regard the ſame may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get many endleſſe ſuites &amp; troubles, they conceive they are fit to be ſeriouſly debated, and finally ended upon the ſetlement.</p>
            <p>5. To the fifth they anſwer that they know of no Forte, or Caſtle that was demoliſhed contrary to articles, And when the particulars ſhall appeare, they will give particular anſwers.</p>
            <p>6. To the ſixt they ſay that the Confederate Catholicks doe receive no profit of their eſtates detayned from them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conceive it not equall that the proteſtants ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the profits of their eſtates, untill after ſetlement, and then the profits of both eſtates, are to be reciprocally received by all parties reſpectively in ſuch manner as ſhalbe agreed upon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rejection_of_response">
            <head>Reaſons why His Majeſties ſaid Roman Catholicke ſubjects are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the anſwers delivered them by his Excellencie the Lord Marques of Ormond, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, his Majeſties Commiſsioner, to certaine Propoſitions by them preſented to his Lordship, on the fourth of September in the twentieth yeare of his Majeſties raigne.</head>
            <p>IN aſmuch as moſt of the reaſons declaring how the ſaid anſwers are not ſatisfactory, doe appeare eyther in the ſaid propoſitions themſelves, or in the reaſons afterwards in the moneth aforeſaid preſented to your Lordſhip, ſetting forth the neceſſity of the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104672:37"/> to avoyd reiteration, what is in the ſaid propoſitions or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons expreſſed, is herein omitted. It is therfore hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly deſired that your Lordſhip in your conſideration of the reaſons now preſented will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly &amp; apart reflect upon the ſaid former propoſitions &amp; reaſons.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Catholickes upon exact ſcrutiny, and ſearch by them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons against the first Anſwer.</hi>
               </note> made of their conſciences and actions, finding nothing more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by the one, nor aymed at by the other (next to the homage which they owe to the King of kings) then the advancement of his Maieſties ſervice, &amp; the ſetling of a full peace &amp; quiet in this his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ireland, they do therfore with heavineſſe of heart apprehend ſome expreſſions in the firſt anſwer (viz. <hi>If the ſaid Roman Catholicke ſubiects ſhall by their obedience and loyaltie merit his Maieſties favour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection)</hi> whereas the ſaid Roman Catholickes are as obedient &amp; loyall ſubiects to his Maieſty as any other his ſubiects without exception, &amp; whereas their thoughts or actions have never deſerved to put them out of his Maieſties protection, yet the occaſion of their ſaid apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions they may not aſcribe to your Excellency, who is intruſted by his Maieſty with the acting &amp; directing part in this great affaire now in Treaty, but unto ſome inſtrumentall cauſe or other miſtake.</p>
            <p>And as to the reſt of the ſaid firſt anſwer (viz. <hi>That when all demands made by your Lordſhip unto the ſaid Catholicks in his Maiesties behalfe, or on the behalfe of the proteſtant Clergte, and on the behalfe of his Maiesties proteſtant ſubiects, are concluded and vpon ſuch merit, as is before expreſſed, the ſaid Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes ſhall not have cauſe to complaine that leſſe moderation is uſed then in the most favourable of</hi> Queene Elizabeth, <hi>or</hi> King Iames <hi>his times, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie will be further adviſed upon the repeale of the ſtatutes made against the ſaid Catholickes.)</hi> Although the ſaid Roman Catholickes are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of his Maieſties grace and goodneſſe, yet ſo great is the penalty impoſed by ſtatutes of force in this kingdome extending to the goods eſtates, liberties, lives, and corruption of bloud of the ſaid Catholicks that they muſt live in reſtleſſe feares ſo long as thoſe extreme puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hang over them, and in caſe his Maieſty by Letters-patents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his great ſeale, or otherwiſe will declare his Royall pleaſure againſt the execution of thoſe ſtatutes upon the ſaid Catholickes, yet thoſe feares will hardly be removed thereby, ſuch is the malice of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party, who have vowed the totall deſtruction of the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, that their adherents here, though not knowne to be ſuch, will never want will, and cannot want opportunity ſufficient to indict the ſaid Catholicks upon the ſaid ſtatutes; &amp; the Iudges before whom the ſaid indictments are found, by their oath declared by the ſtatute of 18. <hi>Elizab.</hi> will not ſtop or ſuſpend the proceedings of the Court for the great Seale, privy ſeale, or his Maieſties letters writs or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104672:37"/> And your Lordſhip may pleaſe to obſerve that by long experience it is manifeſt that ſince the making of thoſe Lawes, being foure-ſcore and odde yeares, the penalties or forfeytures in them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, have not beene ſo prevalent as to draw them the ſaid Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes from the Religion profeſſed by them and their Anceſtors, and no advantage did in ſo long a tract of time accrue to the Crowne by thoſe ſtatutes. And ſeeing his Maieſty is content that moderation ſhould be uſed towards the ſaid Catholickes, to what purpoſe ſhould the ſaid penall lawes be continued in force, whereas the continuation thereof can produce no other effect, then jealouſies and feares in the mindes of the people.</p>
            <p>A free Parliament is propounded and a new Parliament is meaned <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons againſt the</hi> 2. <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </note> in this anſwer to be granted. It is true that Parliaments in their Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ought to be free, yet ſome examples ſhewing the contrary in this kingdome, and a clauſe in the anſwer, viz. <hi>That the Parliament ſhall be diſsolved upon an attempt onely of propounding any other matter, then ſhall be agreed upon by the Articles of Peace,</hi> which attempt may bee purpoſely done by ſome averſe to peace to diſſolve a Parliament, and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of the ſaid clauſe, <hi>attempt,</hi> doth induce the ſaid Catholickes to ſupplicate the inſerting of a free Parliament, And that all the acts to be concluded on by the treaty may not be tranſmitted into <hi>England,</hi> in regarde the ſubſtance of that which will bee paſſed as acts, without tranſmiſſion are to be inſerted in the articles of peace, which &amp; none other act of Parliament is to paſſe upon the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Poynings</hi> act without tranſmiſſion according to the uſuall manner, wherefore the ſaid ſuſpenſion can bring no manner of prejudice upon his Majeſtie, or the publicke ſervice, and that by the granting thereof the peoples mindes will be much quieted The ſaid Catholicks do therfore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire, that the ſaid act be ſuſpended as is by them propounded.</p>
            <p>If the now pretended Parliament, or eyther of the houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made any Orders or Ordinances to the prejudice of the ſaid <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons against the</hi> 3. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> Catholicks, the ſame Parliament may vacate them &amp; take them off the file; And it is not to be preſumed that any member of Parliament is ſo litle affected to the peace or quiet of the kingdome that he will give oppoſition to the third propoſition, or to his Maieſties direction, or to your Lordſhips requeſt in that behalfe. And the ſaid Catholickes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it neceſſary in point of honour and reputation that no Order or Ordinance to their prejudice may remayne of Record in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if no ſuch Order or Ordinance bee, the propoſition can hardly be denied, wherefore it is humbly deſired, that the anſwer may <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons againſt the</hi> 4. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> be more full and ſatisfactory.</p>
            <p>Vpon conſideration of the fourth propoſition &amp; of the reaſons for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104672:38"/> the ſame, it is humbly deſired this anſwer be enlarged to the greater advantage of the ſaid Catholickes, then is expreſſed; and although his Majeſty cannot avoyde Recordes of this nature by Proclamation, yet when his Majeſty is informed that thoſe indictments and outlawries were done of deſigne to extirpate a Nation, and that in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings it will appeare, and here was practiſed, his Majeſties proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a caſe of this generall concernment declaring his diſlike of ſuch proceedings will be of great conſequence and his direction to the Parliament, to that effect will no doubt, accompliſh the deſire of the ſaid Catholicks contained in this Propoſition, and his Royall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to have the Procurers, Actors, and Plotters of and in the ſaid indictments, and outlawries, and the whole proceedings queſtioned, and the deſigne and practiſe being diſcovered and proved, then the ſaid records and all matters depending hereupon, ought in law and juſtice to bee vacated and taken off the file, and the pardon in the anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer mentioned reſtores neither blood nor eſtate, as it is there ſet downe, and admitting the pardon were by Parliament, it will bee of abſolute neceſſitie to avoid all grants, letter-patents, leaſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acts, letters, or promiſes made to the prejudice of the perſons attainted, and to reſtore them to their blood and eſtate, in which act a clauſe condemning the manner of the procuring of the ſaid indicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and outlawries is thought neceſſary to bee inſerted; and the exception mentioned in the ſaid anſwer, is humbly deſired by the ſaid Catholicks to bee taken off; and the clauſe <hi>viz. (His Majeſty will enlarge his mercy.)</hi> to be made more particular.</p>
            <p>This anſwer is humby deſired to bee made equall to all parties one <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> 5. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> way or other, as it is propounded, and that Catholicks ſhould pay debts due upon them, and looſe the debts due unto them, is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to bee equall.</p>
            <p>By his Majeſties graces of the fourth yeare of his raigne, all the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> 6. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> eſtates in the Province of Conaght, and Countie of Clare, in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Indentures of compoſition made by the late Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> for great and valuable conſiderations, with the Lords and Gentrie of the ſaid Province and Countie, and of the grants and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the late King <hi>Iames</hi> of happy memorie, were to bee confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and made good by act of Parliament, the ſtatute of limitation was then to bee paſſed, which extended to all eſtates in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, therefore no greater rent ought to bee reſerved upon the lands in the ſaid Province or Countie, nor upon the lands in the Counties of Tiperarie and Lyndak, then was anſweared to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in the ſaid fourth yeare of his Majeſties raigne.</p>
            <p>And the great offices intituling his Majeſtie unto the before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104672:38"/> lands, and to many mens eſtates in the County of Wickloe, and to the territorie of Idough in the Countie of Kilkenny, were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by an high hand; the free-holders thereof being in poſſeſſion of their repective eſtates then and for many ages before, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption or queſtion. It is therefore humbly deſired, that thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices bee vacated and taken off the file, by his Majeſties gracious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, his highnes or his patentees being therein onely concerned as to the title found by thoſe offices; And that the ſtatute and limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bee here enacted with a retroſpect to the fourth yeare of his Majeſties raigne, at which time it was promiſed by his Majeſty, to have been paſſed as an act in this Kingdome, and if it had beene ſo done, the ſaid offices had not been found. And that the caſe of the Countie of Wickloe, and the Countie of kilkenny meriting equall juſtice and favour with the reſt, ought not to be diſtinguiſhed from them.</p>
            <p>The clauſe in the ſaid anſwer, concerning Innes of Court, and free-ſchooles, as it is expreſſed in the anſwer, will debarre Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt part of the</hi> 7 <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> ſo long as they are of that Religion, from attaining to the knowledge of the lawes of the land, or any other learning within this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>This anſwer is conceived not to be ſatisfactorie and to generall; and particular inſtances of the markes of his Majeſties favour towards <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> 8 <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid Catholicks is humbly deſired.</p>
            <p>The reaſons againſt this anſwer in all the parts thereof are the ſame, that are urged for the ninth Propoſition, and upon conſideration of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>To the</hi> 9. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> thoſe reaſons, the anſwer is humbly deſired to be enlarged.</p>
            <p>His Maieſties anſwer made to the 25. grievance, in the 17. yeare of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>To the</hi> 10. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> his Majeſties raigne, gives five yeares time to the uneſtated Lords, to acquire eſtates in this Kingdome; It is therefore humbly deſired, that the anſwer may be more ſatisfactory on conſideration of the reaſons for the tenth propoſition, and the ſtate of affaires is ſo altered ſince that time, that upon the now intended generall ſettlement more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and warines is to be uſed then at any time before.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Catholicks doe conceive and affirme in all cleerenes, that the Parliament of Ireland is independent of the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>To the</hi> 11. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> without which independency, this realme could be no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor any Parliaments here neceſſary, nor any ſubject of this Kingdome, ſure of his eſtate, life or liberty, other then at the will and pleaſure of a Parliament, wherein neither Lords, Knights nor Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of this Kingdome, have place or vote, and which vowed the deſtruction of all or moſt of this nation, and unwarrantably aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the power to diſpoſe of their eſtates, by the Statutes of ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104672:39"/> to malignants, and Hollanders. To draw this into any debate or queſtion might prove of moſt dangerous conſequence to this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion And yet a declaration of the Parliament here, and an act as in the propoſition is ſet down, is humbly deſired, in regarde his Maieſty was drawne to give the Royall aſſent to the acts of ſubſcription.</p>
            <p>This anſwer is humbly deſired to be enlarged according to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 12. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> for the twelfth propoſition.</p>
            <p>The rates of ſtaple commodities are humbly deſired to be modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Commiſſioners to be appointed by both houſes of Parliament <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 13. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons for the not continuance of the chiefe governor above three yeares are the ſame urged for the fourteenth propoſition. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 14. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons for the erecting and continuance of trayned Bands are the ſame that are urged for the fifteenth propoſition. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 15. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>This anſwer is humbly deſired to be enlarged, and the act of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion to extend to goods taken of eyther ſide, although the Roman Catholickes ſuffered much more then all others in this warre, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 16. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> your Lordſhip will conſider the reaſons for this propoſition.</p>
            <p>It is of neceſſitie the tryall of the perſons to be excepted be by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> 17. <hi>Anſwer</hi>
               </note> otherwiſe the tryall cannot be indifferent in this caſe.</p>
            <p>Wee deſire notwithſtanding thoſe reaſons to be admitted to ſhew ſuch further and other reaſons, and to adde herevnto what wee ſhal thinke fit touching the matter wherein the anſwers are ſhort, or not ſatisfactory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104672:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
